<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mirrour of religious men, and of godly matrones Exhibited in the golden legends of these six famous and faithfull persons. Abraham &amp; Sara, Isack [&amp;] Rebecca: Iacob [&amp;] Rahel. Very comfortable to be read of all the sonnes and daughters of such faithfull parents according to the promise, for the rectifying of their liues and the confirming of their faith. By I.M. Master in Arts.</title>
            <author>Maxwell, James, b. 1581.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17702</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119447</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854654</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854654</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20087</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07314)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20087)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1387:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mirrour of religious men, and of godly matrones Exhibited in the golden legends of these six famous and faithfull persons. Abraham &amp; Sara, Isack [&amp;] Rebecca: Iacob [&amp;] Rahel. Very comfortable to be read of all the sonnes and daughters of such faithfull parents according to the promise, for the rectifying of their liues and the confirming of their faith. By I.M. Master in Arts.</title>
                  <author>Maxwell, James, b. 1581.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 159, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by E. Alde] for E. White, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the gun, neere the little north dore of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iames Maxwell.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20087:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20087:1"/>
            <p>THE MIRROVR of Religious men, and of godly Matrones.</p>
            <p>EXHIBITED IN THE GOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Legends of theſe ſix fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and faithfull <hi>Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Abraham &amp; Sara,</item>
               <item>Iſack &amp; Rebecca:</item>
               <item>Iacob &amp; Rahel.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Very comfortable to be read of all the ſonnes and daughters of ſuch faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full parents according to the promiſe, for the rectifying of their liues and the <hi>confirming of their faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> I. M. <hi>Maſter in Arts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for E. White, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the gun, neere the little north dore of Pauls. 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20087:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20087:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Bruce-ſprung</hi> noble Lord IOHN, Lord Harington, Baron of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton: and to the <hi>right noble</hi> and worthy, <hi>the Lady</hi> ANNE <hi>his wife, and the moſt vertuous Gouerneſſe of the moſte grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> yong Princeſſe. Madam <hi>ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH</hi> Infanta of Albion, all heauenly and earthly happineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the cuſtome</hi> (right honourable) of ſuch as ſet or ſend out any worke to publike viewe, to make choyſe of ſome worthy Perſon for the patronizing thereof. So that I, being about the publiſhing of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Eſſayes and Meditations of mine, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and diuine, and among others, of this preſent Pamphlet, I began to bethinke my ſelfe of ſome conuenient Patron for the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing thereof. And in end after that I
<pb facs="tcp:20087:3"/>
had conſidered of the nature and kinde of the Subiect ſufficiently; and had weighed with my ſelfe the greatneſſe of your humanity, both towards Schollers and my Countrymen; I was emboldened ſo much the more to publiſh it vnder the combined ſplendor of your vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted illuſtrious names. In it one may ſee as in a cleere <hi>Mirrour</hi> or christall glaſſe, a plaine and liuely repreſentation of the <hi>ſayth, pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> and <hi>deuotion,</hi> of the <hi>vprightnes, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> &amp; <hi>compaſſion;</hi> of the <hi>Temperance, ſobriety,</hi> and <hi>moderation;</hi> and of the <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, induſtrie</hi> &amp; <hi>honeſt conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> of the godly <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women</hi> of olde, &amp; namely of the ſix famous &amp; faithfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, therein more particularly painted out. In whoſe <hi>golden Legends,</hi> I hope the ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt-ſighted ſhal not eſpie ſo much as the ſmalleſt ſpice of any fained fiction, falſhood or he: the which thing no doubt, many will deeme and eſteeme a great rarity in a <hi>gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Legend.</hi> In it one alſo may ſee a perfit patterre and picture of a <hi>perfit Seruant of God</hi> Man or Woman; together with an exemplary proofe of Gods bountifull requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and liberall rewarding of them for their ſeruice. Therein likewiſe is as it were in a
<pb facs="tcp:20087:3"/>
viſible manner expreſſed to the eye, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great care that Almighty God hath of his children, euen of all ſuch as doe commend their eſtate, and commit their affaires vnto his fatherly prouidence. Finally this little <hi>Mirrour</hi> doth afford diuers moral obſeruations and inſtructions, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>68.</hi> touching the chiefe duties that men and women owe vnto God, and likewiſe one vnto another: namely ſuch as doe mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally concerne <hi>huſbands &amp; wiues, parents</hi> and <hi>children, maiſters</hi> and <hi>Seruants.</hi> Conſidering then that the nature of it is ſuch and that it may ſerue ſomewhat for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of men and women, chiefely thoſe of the yonger ſort, in the exerciſe of ſoundnes of beliefe, and of ſincerity of life, I am ſo much the more bold to implore your worthy Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage therein, and to pray your honours in the behalfe thereof to anſwere vnto the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of your two chriſten names, which doe import <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>gracious,</hi> and euen to grace this meane Teſtimonie of a dutifull minde, with your gracious acceptance. The which fauour, if it ſhall pleaſe your honours to afford me; I ſhall be encouraged to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about the ſhewing of ſome more ample ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
<pb facs="tcp:20087:4"/>
of mine obſeruancie towards the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your names. And thus wiſhing in the meane time vnto a gracefull <hi>IOHN</hi> and <hi>ANNA</hi> ſuch felicitie, hap, and honour, as hath befaln vnto <hi>ABRAHAM</hi> &amp; <hi>SARA, ISACK</hi> and <hi>REBECCA, IACOB</hi> and <hi>RAHEL,</hi> whoſe godlines and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes ye doe ſo happily imitate: I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours deuoted to all humble duties, IAMES MAXWELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:20087:4"/>
            <head>A SVMMARIE VIEWE of the chiefe contents of this preſent Legend-booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. OF obedience vnto the Lords voyce. page 1. 2. 3. 4. 5.</item>
               <item>II. Of faith in God, &amp; of the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull effects thereof. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11 35. 36. 37. 38. 39. 40. 41. 42. 43. 45. 46. 47. 48. 49. 50. 51. 52. 61. 62. 63. 64. 65.</item>
               <item>III. Of the religious care that ſhould be in Parents for their children, and in Maſters &amp; miſtreſſes for their ſeruants. p. 12. 13. 14. 139. 142. 143. 144. 145 146. 147. 148. 149. 150. 151. 152. 153. 154. 155. 156. 157. 158.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20087:5"/>IIII. Of the qualities of a good Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant. P. 14. 15. 16. 17.</item>
               <item>V. Of the charity, pitty, compaſſion, equity, and peaceable diſpoſition that ought to be in chriſtians. P. 18. 19. 20. 21. 22. 23. 24. 70. 71. 92.</item>
               <item>VI. Of Gods bleſſing and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſuch as ſerue him, and waite on him, p. 3. 25. 26. 27. 28. 57. 58. 59. 65. 66. 67. 68. 76. 107. 116. 119. 120.</item>
               <item>VII. Of Gods raiſing vp of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, and of his caſting downe of the deſpiſers, p. 29. 30. 31. 32. 33. 34.</item>
               <item>VIII. Of the ſubiection, modeſtie, and ſhamefaſtnes, that ought to be in Chriſtian women, p. 52. 53. 79. 80. 81.</item>
               <item>IX. Of Beauty and Bounty in wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. p. 54. 55. 56. 57. 71. 72. 109. 110. 111.</item>
               <item>X. Of Gods preſence &amp; aſſiſtance in the time of the godly mans aduerſity
<pb facs="tcp:20087:5"/>
and affliction. p. 66. 67. 68. 69. 101 102. 123. 124. 126. 127. 130. 131. 132.</item>
               <item>XI. Of diligence and induſtrie that ought to be in Chriſtian men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men p. 73. 74. 104. 105. 106. 111. 112.</item>
               <item>XII. Of the humility and humanity that ought to be in Chriſtian men and women. p. 75. 133. 134.</item>
               <item>XIII. Of the heart-faſting that ought to be in ſuch parties as are about mariage, before that they be hand-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. p. 76. 77. 107.</item>
               <item>XIIII. Of parents and friends bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and well aduiſing of the married couple. p. 78. 79.</item>
               <item>XV. Of the excellency of a vertuous wife, and of the great account that her husband ſhould make of her. p. 82. 83. 84. 88. 93.</item>
               <item>XVI. Of the feruent loue that ought to be betweene married folkes. p. 85. 87. 88.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20087:6"/>XVII. Of the great efficacy of the righteous mans prayer. p. 88. 89. 90. 91.</item>
               <item>XVIII. Of Gods loue and fauour, and of the great efficacy thereof. p. 95. 96. 97. 124. 125. 126.</item>
               <item>XIX. Of the patience, innocency, and modeſty, that ought to be in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. p. 98. 99. 100. 102. 103. 112.</item>
               <item>XX. Of Gods remembring of his children after a ſeeming forgetfulnes, p. 113. 114. 115. 116. 117.</item>
               <item>XXI. Of the Chriſtians patient wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on God, and of the good iſſue thereof. p. 116. 117. 118. 119. 120.</item>
               <item>XXII. Of the thankefulnes that ought to be in Chriſtians towards God for benefits receiued. p. 121. 122. 138. 139.</item>
               <item>XXIII. Of the care and charge that Gods Angels haue of the afflicted and godly. p. 127. 128. 129. 130.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20087:6"/>XXIIII. Of Chriſtians acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of Gods gratiouſnes, and of their owne vnworthines. p. 135. 138.</item>
               <item>XXV. Of the great vanity of Idols, or ſhop-Gods of golde &amp; ſiluer. p. 140. 141. 142.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:20087:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20087:7"/>
            <head>ERRATA,</head>
            <p>Page 8. for vnfalliable, read vnfallible</p>
            <p>Page 19. for vnſoundly. read vnſonnely</p>
            <p>Page 49. for deſeaſed, read deceaſed.</p>
            <p>Page 68 for bended, read bruiſed.</p>
            <p>Page 90. for was, read were.</p>
            <p>Page 100. for opens, read open.</p>
            <p>Page 133. for bleſſeth, read kiſſeth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20087:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20087:8"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The golden legend of ABRAHAM <hi>and</hi> SARA.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Braham</hi> as he was the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the faithfull,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.4, 5, 6. Rom. 4.16, 17, 18.</note> ſo was he more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of all religious and godly rich men. He feared God deuout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, obeyed his voyce readily, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon his name dilligently, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued among men vprightly, and followed his calling carefully.<note place="margin">Gen. 12.1.2.3.4.5.6.7. &amp; 15.1.2.3.4.12.13.18. &amp; 2.17.8.</note> His obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the Lords voyce was ſuch, that he left his natiue country, forſook his kindred and his fathers houſe, and trauailed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20087:9"/>
towards the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 7 2.3 4.5.</note> which the Lord promiſed to giue him &amp; his ſeed: he left a certaine poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for an vncertaine, only relying &amp; repoſing himſelfe vpon the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Gods gratious promiſe. Yea more, when as God had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him a ſon, &amp; one onely ſonne of his wife <hi>Sara,</hi> in their olde age, contrary to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon courſe &amp; ordinary ability of nature,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. and 26. 5. Iames 2.21.</note> he was willing at the Lords voyce to offer him for a burnt offering. So that not without great cauſe is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Patriarks obedience ſo highly commended by the Lords owne mouth. <hi>By my ſelfe haue I ſworne</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>becauſe thou haſt done this thing, and hast not ſpared thine onely ſonne, therfore will I ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſe thee, and will greatly multiply thy ſeed, as the ſtars of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the ſand which is vpon the ſea-ſhore; &amp;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20087:9"/>
thy ſeed ſhal poſſeſſe the gate of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as <hi>Abraham</hi> at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of the moſt high, would haue ſacrificed his ſonne, yea his young ſonne, and his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſonne, and the ſonne of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light; and that with his owne hands, &amp; without protracting of time, (for he roſe vp early in the morning to offer vp his ſon) ſo the Lord in conſideration of his obedience, yea his admirable &amp; memorable obedience, rewarded him moſt amply, and bleſſed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly not onely himſelfe, but likewiſe his ſeed for his ſake.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>1</label>
               </p>
               <p>Hence we may learne this leſſon, that whoſoeuer he be that ſerueth the Lord, hee ſhall finde that hee ſerueth not a thankeles, but a moſt thankefull maiſter, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which he ſaid vnto
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20087:10"/>
                  <hi>Abraham:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Feare not Abraham, I am thy Buckler, and thine exceeding great <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>2</label> reward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Abrahams</hi> obedience in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the Lords voyce and will before the loue of his Country &amp; kindred, yea before the loue of his onely ſon <hi>Iſack,</hi> al his children according to the promiſe, but chiefely rich men, are taught to yeeld obedience vnto the Lords voyce; and euen (if the cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it) to abandon and forſake their deareſt and moſt beloued things, for the cauſe of God, &amp; to preferre his will before al earthly and corruptible treaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 10.37 &amp; 19 29.</note>
                  <hi>He that loueth father or mother more then me</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>is not worthy of me; and he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſonne or daughter more then me, is not worthy of me. And whoſoeuer ſhall forſake houſes, or brethren, or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20087:10"/>
ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children or lands, for my names ſake, he ſhal receaue an hundreth fold more, and ſhall inherit euerlaſting life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well knew holy <hi>Abraham</hi> this, who as he reioyced to ſee Chriſt in the fleſh,<note place="margin">Iohn 8.56</note> ſo he loued him farre aboue all fleſhly and corruptible things: he knew well what it was to be worthy of Chriſt, &amp; would haue rather forſaken all, then to haue proued vnworthy of him that made all.</p>
               <p>This great obedience in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> did flowe from his exceeding great faith, as the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> lets vs to vnderſtand, <hi>By faith Abraham when he was called,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. 11 8, 9, 10 17, 18, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed God, to go out into a place, which he ſhould afterward receaue for inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and he went out not knowing whether he went. By faith he abode in the land of promiſe, as in ſtrange
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20087:11"/>
countrie, as one that dwelt in Tents with Iſack and Iacob, heires with him of the ſame promiſe, for he looked for a Citie hauing a foundation, whoſe builder and maker is God. By faith he offered vp Iſack, when he was tried, and he that had receiued the promiſes, offered his onely begotten ſonne. To whome it was ſaid, in Iſack ſhall thy ſeede be called, for he conſidered that God was able to raiſe him vp euen from the dead, from whence he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him alſo after a ſort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 15.6 and 17.11 23, 24, 25 26, 27 Rom. 4.3.11.16, 17 18, 19, 20 21, 22. Gala. 3.6 Iam. 2.23.</note>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> beleeued God (ſaith the ſcripture) and it was counted to him for righteouſnes, who aboue hope, beleeued vnder hope, that he ſhould be the father of many nations. Neither did he doubt of the promiſe of God thorough vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, but was ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthened in the faith, &amp; gaue glory to God, being fully aſſured that he which had
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20087:11"/>
promiſed was alſo able to do it.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Abraham</hi> had not by inheritance, ſo much as one foote breadth in the land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> yet he beleeued that the Lord was both able and willing, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his promiſe made to him and his ſeede, touching the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereof. Though he knew that <hi>Sara</hi> his wife, being both bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and olde, could not by the courſe of nature conceiue; yet he was aſſured that God was able to giue him a Sonne, euen of her. Finally, though he was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to offer vp his Sonne <hi>Iſack</hi> for a burnt offering vnto the Lord; yet being ſtrengthned in the faith, he conſidered how that God was able to raiſe him vp, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from the dead; and was fully perſwaded that Gods promiſe made to him touching <hi>Iſack</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20087:12"/>
his ſeede, ſhould not, nor could not fall to the ground, and want the owne performance in the own due time. Heauen and earth ſhall paſſe away, but Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is as vnfaileable and vnfalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as God himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham,</hi> if he had beene feeble in the faith, would haue ſaid, what a kinde of a Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is this, for a father to be the ſlayer of his owne Sonne? Haue I receiued a Sonne, and but one Sonne onely, after ſo long prayer, and expectation: and muſt I, and none other but I be the butcher of his body, the ſpiller of his blood, and the burner of his bones? Good Lord what an hard and heauy commandement is this? Is it poſſible O heauens, that God ſhould be the author thereof? How much more like
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20087:12"/>
is this ſon-offering voice vnto the voyce of ſome monſtrous <hi>Milcom</hi> or <hi>Molech,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leuit. 18 21.</note> the blood-ſucking Idol of <hi>Ammon,</hi> rather then vnto the voyce of the moſt gracious God of <hi>Abraham?</hi> chiefly, he hauing promiſed in <hi>Iſacks</hi> ſeede to call and bleſſe all the nations of the earth? and muſt I, and none but I, who was the inſtrument of his life, now be the mortall and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall inſtrument of his death? O my beloued Sonne <hi>Iſack,</hi> would God thou hadſt neuer beene borne: and thou my ſweete wife <hi>Sara,</hi> would God thou hadſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies beene barren, rather then to haue borne a ſon in thine old age after ſo long barrennes, whome thy husband, and his father, muſt now in ſo vnfatherly a faſhion, bereaue of his naturall being and breath.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20087:13"/>But <hi>Abraham</hi> was farre from all ſuch infirmitie, and imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith; and therefore belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that Gods promiſe ſhould not miſſe of performance, but that he was euen able to raiſe <hi>Iſack</hi> againe out of his owne aſhes; he delayed not to doe that which the Lord had enioyned him concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his ſon.<note place="margin">Gen. 22.1. to 13.</note> But when as he was in heauing vp his hand to giue him the mortall blowe with the knife; behold the Angell of the Lord from heauen forbid him to lay his hand vpon the childe. <hi>For now I knowe (quoth he) that thou fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt God, ſeeing that for my ſake thou haſt not ſpared thine onely ſonne.</hi> And thus <hi>Abrahams</hi> will to offer his onely ſonne for a burnt offering vnto the Lord was accepted for the deede.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abrahams</hi> obedience then was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20087:13"/>
correſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dent to his faith, whence it did flowe: his faith was great, and therefore great was his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience;<note place="margin">Io. 8.56.</note> he ſaw <hi>Chriſt</hi> but a farre off, and he was glad: he ſaw by faith, and that a great faith, and therefore great was his ſight, his gladnes and his ioy. And as he had a great faith in his heart, ſo made he a great demonſtration thereof in the actions of his hands.<note place="margin">Gen. 12.7.8. &amp; 13.4.18.</note> For <hi>Abraham</hi> whereſoeuer he ſoiourned, erected an Alter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and called vpon his name. As he forſooke the Idols of his fathers, euen their Gods,<note place="margin">Ioſh. 24.2.3.</note> which were no Gods, ſo he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and worſhiped entierly, the onely true God.<note place="margin">Gen. 14 18 19.20. Heb. 7.4.8.</note> Alſo he payed Tithes vnto <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> the high Prieſt of the moſt high.</p>
               <p>Giuing therby an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to al his <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>3</label> children,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.18.</note> of ſhewing their faith
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20087:14"/>
by their workes: and namely vnto the richer ſort, of conſecrating a part of their ſubſtance to the building &amp; repairing of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, for the ſeruice of God, and of making his miniſters partakers of their goods according as the Apoſtles exhortation doth beare ſaying;<note place="margin">Galat. 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Let him that is taught in the word make him that hath taught him partaker of all his goods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And not onely was <hi>Abraham</hi> religious and godly in himſelfe, but he was alſo carefull for all ſuch as were vnder his charge,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.23.24.25.26.27. Deut. 10.16 &amp; 30.6 Ierem 4.4. &amp; 6.10 Act. 7 51 Gen 18.19</note> to wit for his children and ſeruants, that they ſhould liue before God, as men no leſſe circumciſed in their hearts, then in their fleſh. <hi>I know (ſaid the Lord) that Abraham will command his Sonnes, and his houſholde after him, that they keepe the way of the Lord to doe righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20087:14"/>
and iudgement.</hi> Whereby the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>4</label> children of <hi>Abraham</hi> after the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and chiefly all fathers and maiſters of families, are taught to giue diligence that their children and ſeruants be inſtructed in the knowledge of the true God,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.12.</note> and of godlines, that they may liue godlily, ſoberly, and iuſtly in this preſent world. And the effect of this his chriſtian care for his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie, may appeare, both in his Sonne <hi>Iſack,</hi> and in his ſeruant <hi>Eliezer</hi> of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> the ſteward of his houſe: as for his ſonne, as he was conſecrated to the Lord in his very child-hoode,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.2.10.11.12. &amp; 26.25. &amp; 25.5.</note> ſo was the whole time of his life ſpent in a ſpirituall and reaſonable ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of himſelfe to the Lords ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. Neuer was there a ſonne begotten of man more father like then was godly <hi>Iſack,</hi> who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20087:15"/>
the foote-ſteps of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers faith, pietie, charitie, equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and vertuous liuing; and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded both to his goodnes, and his goods: to his godlines no leſſe then to his gold.</p>
               <p>And as for <hi>Abrahams</hi> chiefe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Eliezer,</hi> his pietie, and fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, are both of them mentioned in the ſcripture to his praiſe. His piety towards God doth appeare in this, that being ſent by <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to take a wife for his ſonne <hi>Iſack</hi> in his owne kinred,<note place="margin">Gen. 15.2.3. &amp; 24.1.2.10.11.12.42.</note> he no ſooner receiued his maſters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, but as ſoone he commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his way and affaires to Gods prouidence, and bleſſing by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: The which thing he did like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, when he was arriued to the Citie of <hi>Nahor, O Lord of my maiſter Abraham, (quoth he) I beſeech thee ſend me good ſpeede this day, and ſhew
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20087:15"/>
mercie vnto my maiſter Abraham.</hi> Such as the maiſter was, ſuch was the man: a religious maiſter and <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>5</label> a religious man, whoſe pietie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God may ſerue for a leſſon to all maiſters and men, to begin alwaies their important affaires at God, by in calling of his name: for except God bleſſe, man cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſhall miſſe, and miſcarrie in his deſignes. Likewiſe <hi>Eliezer</hi> when as he had receiued the ſigne which he had asked of the Lord, to know thereby the proſperous ſucceſſe of his iourney, being ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to the Citie of <hi>Nahor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 24.48.50 51.52.</note> where <hi>Bethuel</hi> dwelt: he bowed himſelfe and worſhiped the Lord, and ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of my maiſter Abraham, which hath not withdrawen his mercy and his truth from my mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: for when I was in the way, the Lord brought me to my maiſters bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20087:16"/>
houſe.</hi> The like was his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and Godly demeanour, when as his errand had taken the deſired effect, and that he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothed <hi>Rekekath,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Bethuel</hi> to his maiſters ſonne <hi>Iſack,</hi> to be his wife.</p>
               <p>Thus godly <hi>Eliezer,</hi> as he began his buſines, in praying vnto God for good ſucceſſe, ſo he ended it, in prayſing God for the good ſucceſſe already gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The which pietie of <hi>Eliezer</hi> is to be practiſed of all good ſeruants, yea, and of all maiſters too. To the end that God, who is the Alpha and the Omega,<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.8.</note> that is to ſay, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp; the ending of all things, may be likewiſe the Alpha and the Omega, of all our actions. <hi>Whether ye eate or drinke</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>or what ſoeuer ye doe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.31. Col. 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>do all to the glory of God, and in the name
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20087:16"/>
of the Lord Ieſus, giuing thankes to God euen the father by him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as this good <hi>Eliezer</hi> was pious towards God, ſo was he no leſſe officious, and faithfull to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his maiſter the father of the faithfull. For both he would not ſo much as eate a crumme of bread in <hi>Bethuels</hi> houſe till he had ſaid his meſſage,<note place="margin">Gen. 24.33 37.54.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.59.61.63 64.</note> and done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his oath; and when as he had done the errand which he came for, and had obtained <hi>Rekekah</hi> for <hi>Iſack,</hi> he would not ſoiourne any longer in <hi>Bethuels</hi> houſe, but departed the next morning, bringing home with him the vertuo us <hi>Rekekah</hi> to god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Iſack;</hi> who as he went out to pray in the fielde toward the euening, met her comming home. And heere againe in this good ſeruant <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>6</label>
                  <hi>Eliezer</hi> are all ſeruants taught to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20087:17"/>
doe all diligence, and to vſe all fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and conſionable carefulnes in doing of their maiſters affaires.</p>
               <p>But to returne from the man to the maiſter; as <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, was not a dead or idle faith, in the behalfe of God (for we ſee it wrought by obedience,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.21.22. Galat. 5.6.</note> and pious liuing in Gods behalfe) ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe was it not dead or idle in the regard of man, but wrought by charitie,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.1.2.3. &amp; 4.19.3.</note> equitie, and loue. This appeareth by his hoſpitality, for he was wont to ſit at the doore of his Tent to inuite ſtrangers, and to bid the poore into his houſe. So that on a time he receiued Angels for his gueſts, at vnwares. And the like did his brothers ſon <hi>Lot.</hi> Whereupon the Apoſtle to the <hi>Ebrewes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13.2.</note> giueth out this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation. <hi>Be not forgetfull to lodge ſtrangers, for thereby ſome haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20087:17"/>
Angels into their houſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>7</label> If then the father of the faithfull, had this godly cuſtome to ſit at his doore, to bid the ſtranger and the poore into his houſe, how vnſeemely and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoundly a thing is it for the ſons and daughters of ſuch a father to be ſo farre from bidding or brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them into our houſes, as not to receiue or entertaine them when they come, but euen to chaſe them away from our doors? The world is now adaies grown ſo Keycolde in charitie, that if the verie Angels themſelues ſhould come downe from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into our houſes, as of olde, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, we would be more ready to bid them to be gone, then to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour them with <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot.</hi> But heare what our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>If ye were Abrahams children ye</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.39.</note>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:20087:18"/>
                  <hi>would doe the workes of Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> was likewiſe full of tender hartednes, pittie, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, toward the miſerable and afflicted: whence it came to paſſe that he not onely deliuered <hi>Lot</hi> from captiuitie,<note place="margin">Gen. 14.12 16 &amp; 18.23.</note> being taken and ſpoiled by <hi>Chedar Laomer</hi> in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of <hi>Sodome</hi> and reſtored him againe to his owne; but he alſo prayed very earneſtly vnto <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>8</label> God for the ſinfull people of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> Whereby the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> are taught to comfort the comfortles, to pittie the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, to deliuer the diſtreſſed, to aide the weake, to ranſome and redeeme the captiue, and to pray for the conuerſion &amp; ſaluation of all men, be they neuer ſo wicked. Yea <hi>Abraham</hi> prayed alſo euen for ſuch men as had don him wrong,<note place="margin">Gen. 20.3.7.17.18.</note> as for king <hi>Abimelech</hi> and his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20087:18"/>
houſhold, when as the Lord had plagued them for taking away <hi>Abrahams</hi> wife from him. Giuing <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>9</label> vs therein an example of praying, euen for our ill-willers and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, according to the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of our Sauiour; <hi>Loue your enemies, bleſſe them that curſe you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.44.45.</note> 
                  <hi>doe good to them that hate you, and pray for them which hurt you and perſecute you, that ye may be the children of your father which is in heauen; for he maketh his ſun to ariſe on the euill, and the good, and ſendeth raine on the iuſt, and the vniuſt.</hi> If we be the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Abraham,</hi> we will do the workes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and if we be the children of God, we will doe the will of our Father which is in heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abrahams</hi> peaceable and milde diſpoſition appeareth in that,<note place="margin">Gen. 13.5. to 12.</note> when as the land was not able to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20087:19"/>
beare him and his brothers ſonne <hi>Lot</hi> to liue together, by reaſon of the great increaſe of their ſtore; he to auoide contention and ſtrife, parted company very lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly with <hi>Lot. Let there be no ſtrife, I pray thee (ſaid Abraham to Lot) betweene thee and me, neither betweene mine Heard-men, and thine, for we be brethren.</hi> Yea, <hi>Abraham</hi> to purchaſe peace reſigned his owne right, and bid <hi>Lot</hi> chooſe what part of the land he did moſt like. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>10</label> Teaching thereby all his children to auoyd all occaſions of wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and contending with their kinſ-men, neighbours &amp; friends, and rather be content to looſe a part of their owne, then enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to quarrell with them for that which iuſtly is theirs. To which purpoſe,<note place="margin">Ro. 12.18.</note> the Apoſtle exhorteth all Chriſtians to labour by all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20087:19"/>
meanes to haue peace with all men. The good chriſtian then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the example of his father <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> will ſhew him-ſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies peaceable: that is a louer, a maker, and a taker of peace. He will cut off all occaſions of contention as much as he can, and he will ſay vnto ſuch a one as would be at debate with him, let there be no ſtrife nor debate I pray thee betweene thee, and me, neither betweene any of ours: for we be brethren, we be Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, euen children of one father, ſeruants of one Lord, fellowes of one Baptiſme, followers of one faith, and members of one mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Church. And in ſo doing, we ſhall be called, not onely the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but euen the ſonnes and daughters of the moſt high, euen of the God of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.9.</note>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:20087:20"/>
As <hi>Abraham</hi> was peaceable, ſo was he likewiſe equitable and iuſt; he would not receiue at the hands of <hi>Ephron</hi> the Hittite a field which he had offered him freely to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie his wife <hi>Sara</hi> in;<note place="margin">Gen. 23.</note> but would needes giue him the price there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, euen foure hundred ſheckles of Siluer. What ſhall we then ſay <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>11</label> of violent oppreſſours, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors of other folkes rights, of robbers, and wrongfull with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders of that which appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to other men? how can ſuch vnreaſonable, and vnequitable vſurpers and encroachers, claime to be called or accounted the children of righteous <hi>Abraham?</hi> If they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> children, they would not take another mans goods for nought, although being offered them by the owner: much leſſe would they violently
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20087:20"/>
bereaue a man of that which is his owne, or yet with hold it from him, they hauing it in their hands. And if ſuch men cannot claime to be <hi>Abrahams</hi> children, how can they make claime to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part or portion in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome? ſeeing the man that would repoſe in <hi>Abrahams</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome after this life,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.22 25.</note> muſt heere in this life harbour in his heart, and beare in his boſome <hi>Abrahams</hi> liuing faith, which was made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite through workes,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.21.22.</note> &amp; wrought by obedience, equitie, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, charitie, and loue.</p>
               <p>But did this godly and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpoſition of <hi>Abraham,</hi> want a reward? No truly; <hi>I will make of thee a great nation (ſaid the Lord) and I will bleſſe thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 12.2, 3.7. &amp; 15 1.2.3 4 &amp; 17.1.4. &amp; 18.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and make thy name great, and thou ſhalt be a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. I will alſo bleſſe them that bleſse
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20087:21"/>
thee, and curſe them that curſe thee, and in thee ſhall all the families of the earth be bleſsed: feare not Abraham, I am thy buckler, and thine exceeding great reward.</hi> The Lord honoured him often with his preſence, in appearing &amp; ſpeaking vnto him: he made him of <hi>Abram, Abraham,</hi> of a father, the father, euen the father of many nations, &amp; digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied him with the title and ſtile to be called the father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; the freind of God.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.17 Iam. 2.23</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham was a great father of many people (ſaith Eccleſiaſticus in) glory was there none like vnto him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccluſ. 45 19.20.21</note> 
                  <hi>He kept the law of the moſt high, and was in couenant with him, &amp; he ſet the couenant in his fleſh, and in tentation he was found faithfull. Therefore he aſſured him by an oath, that he would bleſſe the nations in his ſeed; and that he would multiplie him as the duſt of the earth, and exalt his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20087:21"/>
ſeede as the ſtars, and cauſe them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite, from ſea to ſea, &amp; from the riuer vnto the end of the world.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.30.</note> 
                  <hi>Them that honour mee, I will honour ſaith the Lord. Abraham</hi> honoured and <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>12</label> magnified the God of Iſrael, and therefore God honoured him, and made him the father of the moſt honorable on earth. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> bleſſed the Lord deuoutly at all times, acknowledging all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes, to flowe from him, and God crowned him with aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, both of ſpirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall bleſſings.</p>
               <p>Among other, he bleſſed him with a vertuous and godly wife, whoſe faith towards God, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience towards her husband, are both of them highly extolled in holy ſcripture.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.12</note> 
                  <hi>Through faith</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Sara alſo recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſtrength to conceiue ſeede, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20087:22"/>
was deliuered of a child when as ſhe was paſt age, becauſe ſhe iudged him faithfull which had promiſed.</hi> The tenure of which promiſe is ſet down in theſe words,<note place="margin">Gen 17.19 &amp; 18.10.11 12 13.14 and 21.1.2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Sara thy wife ſhall beare thee a ſonne, and thou ſhalt call his name Iſack, and I will eſtabliſh my couenant with him for an euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing couenant, and with his ſeede after him.</hi> And as the Lord promiſed her a ſonne, ſo he performed his promiſe, and after long barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>13</label> made her to beare euen in her olde age. To teach the ſonnes and daughters of faithfull <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Sara,</hi> not to tie God vnto the ſtrict order of nature, nor to meaſure his power according to the ordinarie ability of naturall cauſes, For God as he is the Lord of Nature, &amp; ſhe his hand-maide, ſo can he worke both without her, and with her, aſwell without
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20087:22"/>
meanes, and contrary to meanes, as with, or according to meanes.<note place="margin">Gen. 16.1.2.3.4</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sara</hi> was deſpiſed in the eyes of her hand-maide <hi>Hagar</hi> for her barrennes: But the Lord at laſt comforted, and cheered vp ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull <hi>Sarai,</hi> and turned her ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes into gladnes, and her mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into mirth: he euen changed her name,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.15.16.19.21.</note> and the inability of her nature both at once. <hi>Sarai thy wife,</hi> (ſaid the Lord to <hi>Abraham) thou ſhalt not call Sarai</hi> (which is aſmuch as my miſtriſſe or dame) <hi>but Sarah ſhall he her name,</hi> (which ſignifieth a Princeſſe or miſtris of many) <hi>and I will bleſse her, and will alſo giue thee a ſonne of her, yea I will bleſse her and ſhe ſhall be them other of Nations, Kings alſo of people ſhall come of her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sara,</hi> I ſay, was barren and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed for her barrennes, euen at the hands of <hi>Hagar</hi> her owne
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20087:23"/>
hand-maide. But the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred her in end, and remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both theſe euills: he made her the mother of <hi>Iſack,</hi> euen the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie mother, of a moſt happie ſonne, (for with him the Lord did eſtabliſh his couenant) and ſo tooke away her barrennes, and reproch; yea more, he made her the honorable Grand-mother of Kings and of Queenes; and ſo not onely tooke away her deſpiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but alſo heaped much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour vpon her head: and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent hand-maide <hi>Hagar,</hi> who before had deſpiſed her daine was turned out a doores with her mocking ſonne <hi>Iſmael.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 16.4.5. &amp; 21.9.10.11.12 13.14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>14</label> Hence we learne two nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble leſſons; one is, that ſuch as God hath imparted any excellent quallitie vnto, or beſtowed vpon any abilitie of nature or of grace,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20087:23"/>
that they beware of deſpiſing ſuch as God hath not dealt ſo liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with.<note place="margin">Pro. 3.34. 1. Pet. 5.5. Iam. 4.6.</note> For God who <hi>reſisteth the proude, and giueth grace vnto the humble,</hi> will deſpiſe the deſpiſers, and exalt the deſpiſed: he will ſcorne the ſcornfull, and curſe ſuch as ſit in the ſeate of the ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. <hi>With the froward,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 18.26</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord will ſhew himſelfe froward,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 3.34</note> 
                  <hi>ſaith holy Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid: and with the ſcornefull he ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, or will ſhew himſelfe ſcornefull,</hi> ſaith wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne. <hi>He that dwelleth in the heauen ſhall laugh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord ſhall haue them in deriſion.</hi> As deſpiſing <hi>Hagar</hi> together with her mocking ſonne <hi>Iſmael</hi> were caſt out of <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe, So ſhall all proud, deſpiſing <hi>Hagars,</hi> &amp; all inſolent mocking <hi>Iſmaels</hi> be debarred from <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome. Wherefore ſeeing that (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh) we are not Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20087:24"/>
of the ſeruant, but of the free woman:<note place="margin">Gal. 4.28.29.30.31.</note> children of the promiſe after the manner of <hi>Iſack,</hi> and not children of the bond woman after the manner of <hi>Iſmael:</hi> let vs ſhew our ſelues not offerers of deſpiſement and mockage with <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Iſmael,</hi> but rather ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers with <hi>Sara</hi> and <hi>Iſack,</hi> that we may be partakers of the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>15</label> The other leſſon we learne hence is this; that the ſonnes and daughters of faithfull <hi>Abraham and Sara,</hi> are taught to commit their cauſe, &amp; to commend their afflicted, and vilipended eſtate vnto God, who is alwaies wont to be neareſt, then, when as his ſeruants by reaſon of the greatnes of their anguiſh and griefe thinke him fartheſt off.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> was ſo farre deſpiſed by his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20087:24"/>
enemies that he calleth him ſelfe a worme, and not a man,<note place="margin">Pſal, 22.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.22.23.24.</note> a ſhame of men, and the contempt of the people, and one that was had in deriſion of all: and his recourſe was vnto God, who drew him out of the wombe, and gaue him hope euen at his mothers breaſts. Euen he deliuered his ſoule from the dogges, and bulles of <hi>Baſhan</hi> which had incloſed him about; wherupon the holy man reſolued to praiſe the Lord in the mids of the congregation, &amp; to exhort &amp; encourage others to doe the like. <hi>for he doth not deſpiſe nor abhor the affliction of the poore: neither hideth he his face from him, but when he calleth vnto him he heareth.</hi> In one word,<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.3.</note>
                  <hi>ſuch as hope in him ſhal not be aſhamed.</hi> Wherefore it is good for all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted perſons to draw neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. <hi>It is God</hi> (as the holy wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20087:25"/>
                  <hi>Anna</hi> ſingeth in her ſong) <hi>that maketh both the barren to beare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2 5 6.7.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and the mother of many children to be weake: he maketh poore and maketh rich, bringeth lowe and exhalteth, he raiſeth vp the poore out of the duſt, &amp; lifteth vp the begger from the dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, to ſet them among Princes, and to make them inherite the ſeate of glory.</hi> Thus ſang <hi>Anna</hi> when as ſhe had receiued a ſonne from the Lord;<note place="margin">1. Sam. 6.</note> being before for her barrennes, deſpiſed in the eyes of fruitfull <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninnah</hi> the other of <hi>Elcanas</hi> wiues.</p>
               <p>Thus, as the holy woman <hi>Anna</hi> after long barrennes, and much deſpiſement &amp; reproch,<note place="margin">1. Sam 1.20. &amp; 3.4. &amp; 7.15.16 17 Iudg. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.4.5.7.24.</note> brought forth her <hi>Samuel</hi> to be a Prieſt before the Lord, &amp; a Iudge of his people; and <hi>Manoahs</hi> barren wife her <hi>Sampſon</hi> to be the Lords cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion againſt the <hi>Philiſtims;</hi> &amp; holy <hi>Elizabeth</hi> her <hi>Iohn</hi> to be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerter
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20087:25"/>
of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 1.5.6.7.13.14.15.16.17.57.60.63.76.</note> the Prophet of the moſt high, and the fore-runner of the <hi>Meſſias Ieſus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Marie</hi> the bleſſed Virgine; So godly and vertuous <hi>Sara</hi> after long barrennes, and much reproch bare in her olde age, with <hi>Elizabeth</hi> her <hi>Iſack</hi> to be the heire of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the ſeedſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of all the bleſſed nations of the earth, and the figure and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> according to the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Thus wee ſee; how that faith <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>16</label> which tranſcendeth nature,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.8.</note> and is not of nature, but of grace, not of man, but Gods gift, made <hi>Sara</hi> to beare when as by nature ſhe was barren. As without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God;<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith it was impoſſible for <hi>Sara</hi> to conceiue and beare a Son in her olde age. And God that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20087:26"/>
doth vnto euery man according to his faith,<note place="margin">Mat 9.29.</note> wrought with vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Sara</hi> according to her faith. As <hi>Abraham aboue hope beleeued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hope that he ſhould be the father of many nations,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4.18.19.21.</note> 
                  <hi>being ſtrengthened in the faith, and not conſidering the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his owne body:</hi> So his wife, <hi>Sara being ſtrengthened in the ſame faith, and not conſidering the deadnes of her wombe, aboue hope beleeued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hope that ſhe ſhould be the mother of many Nations.</hi> Both of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued him, that had promiſed to be both faithfull in his promiſe, and powerfull to performe it.</p>
               <p>Hence we may learne of how great vertue, efficacie and force faith is. By faith a man is counted <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>17</label> righteous before God, for <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> beleeued in the Lord (ſaith the ſcripture) and it was counted vnto him for righteouſnes.<note place="margin">Gen. 15.6. Rom. 4.3 9.</note> By
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20087:26"/>
faith a man hath peace towards God, and pleaſeth him,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.10. Heb. 11.6.</note> and ſo commeth neere vnto him, and <hi>without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle.<note place="margin">Act. 26.18.</note> By faith we are raiſed vp from ſin, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue forgiuenes thereof, &amp; inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance among the Saints:<note place="margin">Act. 15.9.</note> by faith our hearts are purified, and clenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>and Bleſſed be the pure in heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.8.</note> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> By faith we are ſtrenthened in Gods grace, we reſiſt the deuil,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.2.5.9. &amp; 5.9.</note> the world and the fleſh, yea, we ouercome them;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.12 Galat 3.14 26. Epheſ. 2.8, 9. 2. Tim. 3.15. 2. King. 6.14.15, 16.17</note> we haue free ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe vnto God, we receiue his bleſſing, we are made his ſonnes, and in end we acquire the ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſoules. <hi>Eliſha</hi> was ſo ſtrong in faith, that he feared not the troupes of the King of <hi>Siria,</hi> that he ſent out to apprehend him. <hi>Feare not</hi> (quoth the Prophet
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20087:27"/>
to his ſeruant being affrayed of the mighty hoſt of their enemies) <hi>for they that be with vs, are more then they that be with them.</hi> The Citie of <hi>Dothan</hi> was compaſſed with Horſes and charets, ſent by the King of <hi>Syria</hi> to offend <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and to apprehend him. But loe, the mountaine was full of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Charets of fire round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſent by the King of Kings to defend his ſeruant, and to confound his foes. <hi>The Angel of the Lord</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>pitcheth round about them that feare him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.7.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; deliuereth them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 6. to 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Ionathan</hi> accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with his armour-bearer, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fited the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> through the great faith he had in God, <hi>For it is not hard for the Lord to ſaue with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or with few,</hi> quoth <hi>Ionathan</hi> to his man.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.26.32. to 37. &amp; 55.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> being armed with an inuincible faith in God, went out
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20087:27"/>
againſt the mighty <hi>Goliah,</hi> and ſmote him firſt in the fore-head with a ſtone, ſo that he fell groue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to the ground; &amp; afterwards ſmote off his head with his owne ſword. <hi>The Lord that deliuered me</hi> (quoth <hi>Dauid</hi> to King <hi>Saul) out of the paw of the Lion, and out of the paw of the beare, he will deliuer mee out of the hands of this Philiſtim.</hi> No, the Lord not onely deliuered <hi>Dauid</hi> out of his hands, but alſo deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the vncircumciſed <hi>Philistim</hi> into the hands of his champion <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The three children by their faith in God were preſerued in the middes of the firie fornace.<note place="margin">Dan. 3.16.17.27.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaid they to the King) <hi>our God whome we ſerue is able to deliuer vs from the hot fierie fornace, and he will deliuer vs out of thine hand, O King!</hi> And according to their
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20087:28"/>
ſaith, ſo it fell out; for the fire had no power ouer their bodies, no not ſo much as an haire of their head was burnt, neither were their coates changed, no not ſo much as any ſmoakie ſmell of fire came vpon them. They were caſten bound into the mids of the hote fierie fornace; but loe, the king ſeeth them looſe walking in the mids of the fire, as if it had beene amids a glorious and a freſh flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing garden, together with one in their companie like the Sonne of God. Their faith in God made the fierie fornace vnto them as a freſh medow, when as the flame thereof conſumed the Idolatrous and faithles officers that threw them in: a wonderfull worke, that the fire ſhould forbeare to burne the ſmalleſt haire of the head of ſuch as were caſt into the mids of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20087:28"/>
it, and in the meane while deſtroy and ſlay ſuch as were without it. The ſeruants of God were ſafe in the fire becauſe of their faith in God: but the kings ſeruants though being without the fire, were not yet ſafe, becauſe they were without faith in God. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon <hi>Nebuchadnezzer</hi> the king was conſtrained to praiſe God, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed be the God of Shadrach Meſhach, and abednago, who hath ſent his Angell, and deliuered his ſeruants that put their truſt in him.</hi> And not onely did he bleſſe God for them, but alſo decreed, that whoſoeuer ſhould ſpeake any blaſphemie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, that he ſhould be drawne in peeces, and his houſe made a Iakes. And withall as he honored and magnified the God of <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach, and Abednago,</hi> acknowledging that there is no
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20087:29"/>
God that can deliuer after this ſort, and commanding all his ſubiects to doe the ſame; ſo did he promote theſe men that thus did honour God, to greate honour in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince of <hi>Babell.</hi> Wherein we finde that ſaying of the Lord verified, <hi>Them that honour me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2 30.</note> 
                  <hi>I will honour.</hi> The like was the efficacie of <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> faith,<note place="margin">Dan. 6.11.12.16.22.23.24.26.27.</note> the ſtrength whereof did ſurmount the ſtrength of the ſtrongeſt beaſtes, euen of <hi>Darius</hi> his Lyons. He was caſt into the Lyons denne, for making his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication vnto God, yet no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of hurt was found on him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he beleeued in God: <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> faith made him ſafe in the mids of the den amongſt a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of hugry deuouring beaſts; wheras they brake all the bones of their accuſers which wanted faith in God, or euer they came at
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20087:29"/>
the ground of the den. Whervpon king <hi>Darius</hi> made a decree, that within all his dominions, men ſhould tremble and feare before the God of <hi>Daniel: for he is the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, and remaineth for euer</hi> (ſaid the king) <hi>and his kingdome ſhall not periſh, and his dominion ſhall be euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. He reſcueth and deliuereth, and he worketh ſignes and wonders in heauen and in earth: who hath deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Daniel from the power of the Lyons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle to the Hebrewes painteth out at large the efficacie of the faith of the men of God of olde.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> Faith opened the heauens to <hi>Enoch,</hi> and freed him from ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of death. Faith preſerued <hi>Noe</hi> and his houſhold from the flood. Faith made the people of God vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conduction of <hi>Moſes</hi> the man of God, to paſſe through the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20087:30"/>
red ſea as by drie land; which when the Egiptians had aſſayed to doe, they were drowned: for they both wanted faith in God themſelues, and they perſecuted ſuch as had faith, and beleeued in God. Likewiſe by faith the walles of <hi>Iericho</hi> fell downe after they were compaſſed about ſeuen dayes. Thus we ſee, faith is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then walled townes, for it maketh them to fall; ſtronger then Lyons and Beares, for it tieth their pawes, and ſhutteth vp their iawes; ſtronger then the raging Sea, and the moſt ouer-flowing floods, for it turneth them into drie land: and ſtronger then the conſuming fire, for it maketh it colde as water, and as refreſhing as a faire flowery field. <hi>The men of God</hi> (ſaith the holy Apoſtle) <hi>through faith ſubdued kingdomes,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20087:30"/>
wrought righteouſneſse, obtained the promiſes, ſtopped the mouthes of Lyons, quenched the violence of fire, eſcaped the edge of the ſword, of weake were made ſtrong, waxed valiant in battell, turned to flight the armies of the aliants: finally, by faith the women receiued their dead children raiſed to life.</hi> So that faith is not onely ſtronger then walled townes, then armed men, then roaring Lyons, then the raging ſea, then the flaming fire, but alſo ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then death it ſelfe: Yea,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.9. Epheſ. 6.16 1. Ioh. 5.4.</note> it is ſtronger then the diuell, for it quencheth all his fierie dartes, and maketh him to flie from vs, with the winges of the winde, though his ſtrength far exceede the ſtrength of millions of roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and deuouring Lyons. And as the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes ſetteth before our face the force
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20087:31"/>
of faith in the holy men of olde; So doth the holy Goſpell afford vs diuers notable teſtimonies of the wonderfull effects thereof in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers perſons.<note place="margin">Mat 8.2.3.5.6.8.10.13.14.15.</note> The leaper that came to Chriſt, through faith in him, beleeuing that he was able to make him cleane, was cleanſed of his leproſie with one touch of our Sauiours powerfull finger. And by the ſame faith and finger, was <hi>Peters</hi> mother in lawe cured and freed of her feuer. And the <hi>Centurions</hi> ſeruant was healed of his palſie. <hi>Speake the word onely</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Centurion</hi> to our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) <hi>and my ſeruant ſhall be healed.</hi> Our Sauiour marueiled at his faith, and ſaid vnto his followers, <hi>Verily I haue not found ſo great faith euen in Iſraell:</hi> and vnto the <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion</hi> himſelfe he ſaid; <hi>Goe thy way, and as thou haſt beleeued, ſo be it vnto
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20087:31"/>
thee.</hi> And his ſeruant was healed the ſame houre.<note place="margin">Mat 9.18.20.21.22.25.28.29.30. &amp; 20.30.31.32.33.34.</note> By faith was the woman that had beene twelue yeares ſick of a bloody iſſue, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of her deſeaſe. <hi>for ſhe ſaid in her ſelfe, if I may touch but his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment onely, I ſhall be whole. Then Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus turned him about, and ſeeing her, did ſay, daughter, be of good comfort, thy faith hath made thee whole, and the woman was made whole at that houre.</hi> Her faith was great, and therefore deliuered her from a great deſeaſe, and wrought vpon her a great cure: her faith was preſent, and therefore was ſhe preſently cured without any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting of time.</p>
               <p>It was a matter of good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to her that ſhe was cured of a long and lingring diſeaſe. It was a matter of greater comfort to her that ſhe was cured by the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20087:32"/>
great Phiſition our Sauiour Chriſt. And it was a matter of greateſt comfort of all, that ſhe being a poore patient, ſick in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſinfull in ſoule, became by the meanes of her faith, to be ſo much dignified as to be made and called the daughter of the Sonne of God. <hi>Daughter</hi> (ſaid our Sauiour vnto her) <hi>be of good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, thy faith hath made thee whole.</hi> The like honour and helpe, he vouchſafed vpon the ſick of the palſie ſeing his faith, <hi>Son be of good comfort, thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee,</hi> ſaid our Sauiour vnto the ſinfull, ſick-man: whereupon he aroſe freed from the ſicknes of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the ſinne of his ſoule both at once. <hi>Iairus</hi> the ruler of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue beleeued that our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was able to cure his daughter being deſeaſed, yea to quicken
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20087:32"/>
her being deſeaſed: <hi>My daughter is now dead</hi> (ſaid he to our Sauiour) <hi>but come and laye thine hand on her, and ſhee ſhall liue:</hi> And ſo did the iſſue anſwere vnto his faith, for preſently ſhe reuiued and aroſe. Two blinde men beleeued that our Sauiour was able to reſtore them to their ſight, and their eies were opened as ſoone as he had touched them, and ſaid,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.22 22.</note> 
                  <hi>be it vnto you according to your faith.</hi> And vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Cananitiſh woman whoſe daughter was vexed with a deuill, who did ſue at his hands for helpe with great importunitie and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencie, his anſwere was; <hi>O woman, great is thy faith, be it to thee, as thou deſireſt: and her daughter was made whole at that houre.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat 17.14 15.18. Mat. 9 17 to 30</note> Likewiſe the lunaticke child was healed at the humble petition of his beleeuing father, witout any longer delay:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20087:33"/>
&amp; the Ruler of capernaum his ſon being ſick vnto the death,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.47.50.53.</note> was healed, becauſe of the faith of his father, who beleeued the word that Ieſus had ſpoken vnto him. The holy Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> through faith walked on the water,<note place="margin">Mat. 14.28 29</note> as on the drie land. And the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 14.8 9.10.</note> beholding a certaine impotent man which had beene a creeple from his mothers wombe and had neuer walked, and perceiuing that he had faith to be healed, ſaid with a loud voice, ſtand vpright on thy feete; and he leaped vp and walked. Thus we ſee, how that faith is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make the lame to goe, the blind to ſee, the dumbe to ſpeake, the deafe to heare, the leaper to be cleane, the lunaticke and mad to be in their right minde, and the dead to ariſe. No maruell
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20087:33"/>
then though the ſame faith was able to make <hi>Sara</hi> to beare in her barren olde age: For as our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaid vnto the man whoſe ſon was poſſeſſed,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.23.</note> 
                  <hi>all things are poſſible to him that beleeueth:</hi> and vnto his diſciples;<note place="margin">Mat 21.22</note> 
                  <hi>what ſoeuer ye ſhall aske in prayer, if yee beleeue, ye ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not then without great cauſe that <hi>Moſes</hi> exhorted the people going out to battell,<note place="margin">Deut. 30.3</note> to haue faith in the victorie promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;<note place="margin">1. Sam. 12.20.21.52.</note> that <hi>Samuel</hi> encouraged the people to truſt in God, and that <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> enioyned the people to confide in God,<note place="margin">2. Chron. 20.20.</note> and to beleeue his Prophets: Good cauſe had the holy Apoſtles to deſire of Chriſt to encreaſe their faith,<note place="margin">Luk 17.5.</note> and to exhort men to ſtand ſtedfaſt in the faith,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 16.13. 2 Cor. 13.5.</note> and to prooue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues whether they be in the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20087:34"/>
faith or no,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.17 1. Tim. 6.12.</note> and to grow from faith to faith: Finally, to fight the good fight of faith,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.9.</note> and ſo to lay holde on eternall life, and in end to receiue the end of our faith, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the ſaluation of our ſoules.</p>
               <p>And as <hi>Sara</hi> is greatly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for her faith towards God, ſo likewiſe is ſhe for her obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards her husband, her mildneſſe of ſpirit, and modeſtie in attire: And therefore the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>18</label> Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth all women and wiues to imitate the example of her excellent vertues.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.1.2.3.4.5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Let the wiues be ſubiect to their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, that euen they which obey not the word, may without the word be wonne by the conuerſation of the wiues, while they beholde your pure conuerſation which is with feare: whoſe apparelling let it not be outward as with broyded haire and gold put about
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20087:34"/>
or in putting on of apparell, But let the Hid man of the heart be vncorrupt, with a meeke and quiet ſpirit, which is before God a thing much ſet by. For euen after this manner in time paſt did the holy women which truſted in God ner themſelues, and were ſubiect to their huſbands. As Sara obeyed Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and called him Syr, or Lord, whoſe daughters ye are, whiles ye doe well.<note place="margin">Eccleſi. 26.35.27</note> A ſhamefast woman</hi> (ſaith <hi>Siracides) will reuerence her husband. A woman that honoureth her husband ſhall be iudged wiſe of all: But ſhe that deſpiſeth him, ſhall be blazed for her pride.</hi> This ſame ſubiection, ſhamefaſtnes, and modeſtie of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> in her cariage and cloathing, the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth very earneſtly vnto women in his Epiſtle to <hi>Timothie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.9.10.11.</note> As our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſaid to the Iewes, that if they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> children,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20087:35"/>
they would doe the workes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.39.</note> So may it be ſaid of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and wiues, as many as be the daughters of <hi>Sara,</hi> they will imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the modeſty,<note place="margin">Gen 12.11 14. &amp; 24.16. &amp; 26.7. &amp; 29.17 1. Sam. 25.3.42.</note> meeknes, ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtnes, and obedience of <hi>Sara.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is recorded in ſcripture, that <hi>Sara</hi> was a faire woman to looke vpon, and very beautifull, the like is ſaid of <hi>Rebecca Iſacks</hi> wife, and of <hi>Rahel Iacobs</hi> wife, and of the verteous and wiſe <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaill Dauids</hi> wife, after the death of churliſh <hi>Nabal.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 36.22.23.24</note> The beautie of a woman (ſaith <hi>Ieſus</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Sirach) cheereth the face, and a man loueth nothing better. If there be in her tongue gentleneſſe, meekenes, and wholſome talke, then is not her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band like other men: he that hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a vertuous woman, hath begunne to get a poſseſſion, ſhe is an helpe like vnto himſelfe, and a piller to reſt vpon.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20087:35"/>
As the Sunne when it ariſeth in the high places of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 26.16.17.18</note> 
                  <hi>ſo is the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a good wife the ornament of her houſe: as the cleare light is vpon the holy candleſtick, ſo is the beautie of the face in a ripe age: and as the golden pillers are vpon the ſockets of ſiluer, ſo are faire feete with a conſtant minde.</hi> The externall beautie of <hi>Saras</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die was accompanied with the internall beautie of her minde; and in a faire body in her perſon was lodged a more faire ſoule.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>19</label>
               </p>
               <p>Thus in the example of the beautious and bounteous <hi>Sara</hi> are all matrons &amp; maides admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed to ioyne bountie, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and modeſtie of minde, to the beautie of body, and vertuous carriage to the well-fauourednes of their outward feature. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how that beautie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bountie in a woman (as the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20087:36"/>
wiſe man ſpeaketh) <hi>is as a Iewell of golde in a ſwines noſe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 11.22 &amp; 12.4. &amp; 31.30.</note> and that not the beautious, but the vertuous woman is the crowne of her husband. <hi>For fauour is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and beautie is a vaniſhing thing, but a woman that feareth the Lord ſhe ſhall be praiſed. Houſe and riches may be the inheritance of the fathers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 18.22 &amp;. 19.14.</note> 
                  <hi>but a prudent wife commeth of the Lord: and he that findeth ſuch a wife findeth a good thing, and receiueth fauour of the Lord.</hi> And doubtles <hi>Abraham</hi> who found ſo many good things, and ſo great fauour at the hands of the Lord, he found this fauour, &amp; this cheife good thing, to wit, a good wife amongſt many other fauours and good things.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 26.3.14.15.24</note> 
                  <hi>A vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous woman is a good portion,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Siracides) which ſhall be giuen for a guift vnto ſuch as feare the Lord.</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:20087:36"/>
Who feared the Lord more then did godly <hi>Abraham?</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently what man could there be more worthy of a vertuous wife then hee? There is nothing ſo much worth as a woman well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, and there is no waight to be compared vnto a ſhamefaſt womans peaceable, faithfull, &amp; continent minde: And who could be ſo worthie of ſuch a worthy pearle as the worthieſt amongſt men, the holy Patriarke <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faithfull?</p>
               <p>And as God bleſſed him with a vertuous and an vnderſtanding wife which proued the ioy and crowne of her husband, whoſe death therefore he had great cauſe to bewaile, as he did with mourning and lamentation;<note place="margin">Gen. 23.1.2</note> ſo did he endowe him exceedingly with temporall ſtore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20087:37"/>
and multiplyed him,<note place="margin">Gen. 13.5.6 &amp; 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.36</note> ſo that he gaue him in great aboundance, men-ſeruants and maid-ſeruants, ſiluer and golde, Camells &amp; Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>20</label> Sheepe and Beeues. Wherein we finde that ſaying of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle verified.<note place="margin">1. Tim 4.8</note> 
                  <hi>Godlynes is profitable vnto all things which hath the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the life preſent, and of that which is to come.</hi> Laſtly, the Lord hath ſuch an honorable regard of <hi>Abraham</hi> that according to his promiſe made to him,<note place="margin">Gen. 12.3.</note> ſaying, <hi>I will bleſſe them that bleſse thee, and curſe them that curſe thee.</hi> He both curſed and bleſſed other men for <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſake: As he plagued <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao</hi> king of <hi>Gerar</hi> together with their houſholdes for offering to doe him wrong:<note place="margin">Gen 12.15 16.17.18 19.20. &amp; 20.3.4 7.17.18. &amp; 19.29. &amp; 20.17. &amp; 27 3.4.5.</note> ſo for <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſake and at his entreatie, he mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied <hi>Iſack,</hi> and deliuered <hi>Lot</hi> from the deſtruction of <hi>Sodome,</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:20087:37"/>
and healed king <hi>Abimelech</hi> and all his houſholde. So effectually was God with <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he was alſo with others for <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſake.</p>
               <p>Wherein all the Sonnes and Daughters of faithfull <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sara</hi> may beholde cleerely as in a chriſtall glaſſe, of how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull great vertue and force godlynes is, it being able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a bleſſing at Gods hands, not onely to the godly man himſelfe, but vnto others alſo, euen vnto ſuch as the godly man, either prayeth for, or yet reapeth any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite by. Thus God bleſſed and proſpered <hi>Laban</hi> for <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſake,<note place="margin">Gen. 30.37 &amp; 39.2.3.4.5.6.</note> ſo long as he ſoiourned with him in his houſe. And thus he bleſſed <hi>Putiphar</hi> the Egiptian for <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ſake, and made his bleſſing to reſt vpon all that he had in the houſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20087:38"/>
and in the field: And thus no doubt, but he will bleſſe all ſuch as the followers of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.21.22.23.</note> and the workers of his workes (for theſe two God hath conioyned together, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man muſt not ſeuer them) ſhall recommend vnto God in their prayers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:20087:38"/>
               <head>The golden Legend of ISACK and REBECCA.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Sack</hi> the Sonne and heire of faithfull <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and <hi>Sara,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 17.15.16 17 18. &amp; 18.10.11.12.13, 14. &amp; 21.1.2.3. &amp; 25 5 &amp; 26.25.</note> as he was conſecrated to the Lord in his verie childe-hood; ſo was his whole life nothing els but a reall and an actuall ſacrificing of himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lords ſeruice: he walked in the wayes and foot-ſteps of his father, and followed the trace of his faith, pietie, charitie, equitie, and vertuous liuing. He ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded aſwell to his goodnes as to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20087:39"/>
his goods: to his godlines, no leſſe then to his golde: whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he ſpread his Tent, there did he not faile to erect an Alter vnto the Lord, and to call vpon his name. Whereſoeuer he had his chamber, there God had his Church; yea his Tent was a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Tabernacle, &amp; his bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was as a chappel dedicated to the ſeruice of the God of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>22</label>
                  <hi>Abraham.</hi> VVhereby all the children of <hi>Iſack</hi> according to the promiſe are taught to worſhip God not onely publikly in the Church, but alſo priuately in their ſecret chambers. Both which duties the ſweete ſinger of Iſrael doth ioyntly mention in the fourth Pſalme, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth them to our practiſe. The priuate deuotion, in theſe wordes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Examine your owne heart
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20087:39"/>
vpon your bed and be ſtill:</hi> and the publick, in theſe, <hi>offer the ſacrifices of righteouſnes, and truſt in the Lord.</hi> VVhereby he giueth vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that no place whether pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, or publicke, is to be thought vnfit for the practiſing of holy duties: for Gods worſhip as it ſhould be publickly performed in the Church according to that of the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.22 25. &amp; 111.1.</note> 
                  <hi>In the midst of the congregation wil I praiſe thee,</hi> ſo muſt it not be neglected priuatly in the chamber according to which it is written of the Prophet <hi>Daniel that he went into his houſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 6.10.</note> 
                  <hi>and hauing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the window of his chamber that looked toward Ieruſalem, he kneeled vpon his knees three times a day, and prayed and praiſed his God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe two, priuate deuotion, &amp; publicke adoration, God hath conioyned, and therefore man
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20087:40"/>
muſt not ſeuer them. They are as the two hands of our chriſtian profeſſion: the publicke is as the right hand, the priuate as the left; the want of either maketh a mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med chriſtian: And as no place is vnfit for Gods ſeruice, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe no time, whether morning, or euening, night or day. <hi>It is a good thing to praiſe the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 92.1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>and to ſing vnto thy name O moſt high; to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare thy louing kindnes in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and thy truth in the night.</hi> ſaith deuout <hi>Dauid:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal, 119.62.</note> and againe, <hi>at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night will Iriſe to giue thankes vnto thee, becauſe of thy righteous iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Heare my voice in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 5.3.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord, for in the morning will I direct me vnto thee, and I will waite.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe <hi>Siracides</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Eccle. 2.28 &amp; 39.5.</note> that <hi>we ought to preuent the ſunne riſing to giue thankes, and to ſalute the Lord before the day ſpring.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20087:40"/>
The wiſe man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>will giue his heart to reſort early vnto the Lord that made him, and to pray before the moſt high for his ſinnes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 55.17</note> 
                  <hi>Euening and morning, and at noone will I pray,</hi> (ſaith godly <hi>Dauid) and he will heare my voyce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſack</hi> waited on God,<note place="margin">Gen 26.1.2.3.4.5.</note> inuoked him, and walked with him: And therefore God was with him, and prouided for him in the time of famine which was in the land: he honoured the Lord, and the Lord honoured him with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and appearance. For he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared vnto him, and bid him dwell in the land of <hi>Gerer,</hi> and promiſed to bleſſe him; and not him onely, but alſo in his ſeede all the nations of the earth. As he was religious and godly farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other, ſo was God with him, and bleſſed him farre aboue
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20087:41"/>
all other. He both preſerued him in the time of famine, &amp; increaſed his ſubſtance and ſtore. So that when as he ſowed in that land, he found in the ſame yeare an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth folde by eſtimation. <hi>He wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mightie and ſtill increaſed till he was exceeding great.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 26.12 13 14.</note> As he was great in faith, and in godlines grew daily, ſo did he encreaſe from day to day, in his familie and goods: For he had flockes of ſheepe, and heards of cattell, and a mighty houſholde.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gen 26.14 15.16.17.18.19.20.21.22.</note>And though that the Philiſtims among whome he liued, did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie him, and vex him by ſtopping of his welles, and in end draue him away after much ſtrife; yet the Lord was alwayes on his ſide. The Philiſtims were his foes, but the God of Iſrael was his friend: and the man that hath God for
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20087:41"/>
his friend, is ſtrong enough to withſtand all his foes, be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo furious. <hi>Iſack,</hi> when as he was reſiſted by men, was aſſiſted of God:<note place="margin">Gen. 26.23.24.</note> for when as he was thus afflicted by the faithles Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims. God who is faithfull and true, and who loued faithful <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and his ſeede, appeared vnto <hi>Iſack</hi> the ſame night in <hi>Beer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba</hi> and ſaid vnto him thus, <hi>I am the God of Abraham thy father, feare not, for I am with thee, and will bleſse thee, and multiply thy ſeede for my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>23</label> Abrahams ſake.</hi> Happie is the man who with <hi>Iſack</hi> hath the Lord with him, and bleſſed is he whom the Lord bleſſeth: for he needeth not to be affrayed, neither of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, nor infection, nor yet of foes. <hi>Who ſo dwelleth in the ſecret of the moſt high</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>ſhal abide in the ſhadow of the almighty.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 91.1.2.3.4.5.6.7.10.</note>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:20087:42"/>
                  <hi>The Lord will deliuer him from the ſnare of the hunter, and from the noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome peſtilence: he ſhall not be affraid of the feare of the night, nor of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that flyeth by day. There ſhall none euill come vnto him, neither ſhall any plague come neere his tabernacle.</hi> If God be on our ſide, what matter is it who be againſt vs? For what better is their opoſition, then a blowe with a bended reede, or their violence, then a blaſt of winde? <hi>Feare ye not them</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>which kill the body, but are not able to kill the ſoule:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 10.28</note> 
                  <hi>But rather feare him which is able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy both body and ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the Lord as he was ready and preſent to comfort &amp; cheere vp <hi>Iſack</hi> in his affliction; ſo was he not onely his friend himſelfe, But alſo he framed the heart of king <hi>Abimelech</hi> to fauour him.<note place="margin">Gen. 26.26.27.28.29.</note> 
                  <hi>For
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20087:42"/>
the heart of the king is in the hands of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 21.1.</note> 
                  <hi>he turneth whether ſoeuer it pleaſeth him,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon. Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech</hi> of a foe was made a friend to <hi>Iſack,</hi> before he vexed him, but afterwardes he went vnto him to viſit him, and to make an alliance and couenant with him. For we ſaw (quoth the king) that certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Lord was with thee, as if he ſhould haue ſaid, we ſaw God to be with thee, and therefore it was not fit that we ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee: we ſaw God was thy friend, ſo that it was but a follie for vs to be any longer thy foes.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>24</label> Whereby all faithfull folkes are taught, that Gods helpe is moſt preſent, when as mans ayde is moſt abſent: as alſo that if we haue our refuge vnto him in our afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with <hi>Iſack,</hi> God will alſo comfort and cheere vs vp with
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20087:43"/>
                  <hi>Iſack.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.31</note> So that if God be with vs, we ſhall not neede to feare who be againſt vs. For either God will turne the hearts of our foes, and make them our friends, as he did heere with <hi>Iſacks</hi> enemies: or els they ſhall not be able to doe vs any notable harme.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 26.30.31.</note>And as <hi>Abimelech</hi> together with his Philiſtims and friends came to treat of peace, alliance and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie with <hi>Iſack;</hi> So did he on the other part ſhew his peaceable diſpoſition and gentle nature in entertaining them (for he made them a feaſt) and in accepting of the offer made by the king, for they ſware one to another. And truly if we deſire to ſhew our ſelues the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> and of <hi>Iſack:</hi> we muſt behaue our <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>25</label> ſelues ſemblably in the behalfe of our neighbours, by the meanes
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20087:43"/>
of a courteous, gentle, kinde and quiet cariage. In one word, the Apoſtles exhortation to all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, is to haue peace and amitie,<note place="margin">Ro. 12.18.</note> if it be poſſible, with all men. That we may be the children not onely of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſack,</hi> but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the moſt high,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.9.</note> the father of vs all which is in heauen.</p>
               <p>And as God bleſſed <hi>Abraham</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many other bleſſings with a vertuous wife; ſo did he likewiſe his Sonne <hi>Iſack.</hi> For a <hi>prudent wife co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 19.14</note> ſaith <hi>Salomon, and a godly woman is giuen to him that feareth the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 16.14.</note> ſaith <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racides.</hi> Of <hi>Sara</hi> it is ſaid that ſhe was verie faire, and of <hi>Rebecca,</hi> that ſhe was beautifull to the eye,<note place="margin">Gen. 12.14 &amp; 24 16. &amp; 26.7.</note> and verie faire to looke vpon. But this is not all, the externall beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of her body was accompanied with the internall beautie of her
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20087:44"/>
minde; and in both ſhe proued the true daughter of <hi>Sara,</hi> whoſe beautie and bountie are both of them recorded in ſcripture to her praiſe.<note place="margin">Eccleſ 36.22.23.24.</note> 
                  <hi>The beautie of a woman</hi> ſaith <hi>Siracides, cheereth the face, and a man loueth nothing better, if there be in her tongue gentlenes, meeknes, and wholſome talke, then is not her husband like other men.</hi> As <hi>Naomi</hi> ſaid vnto <hi>Ruth, all the Citie of my people doth know that thou art a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous woman,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ruth 3.11.</note> So all the Citie of <hi>Nahor</hi> knew that <hi>Rebecca</hi> liuing as yet in her fathers houſe, was a vertuous and a modeſt maide; and after ſhe was married to <hi>Iſack,</hi> all the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> and of <hi>Gerar</hi> knew that ſhe was a wiſe and a well quallified wife.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 25.8 &amp; 26.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Well is him</hi> (ſaith <hi>Siracides) that dwelleth with a wife of vnderſtanding:</hi> and well was <hi>Iſack</hi> to haue found ſuch a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20087:44"/>
wife as wiſe <hi>Rebecca.</hi> For there is nothing (ſaith the wiſe man) of ſo much worth as a woman well inſtructed. And thus in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>26</label> of <hi>Rebecca</hi> are all matrons and maides taught to ioyne bountie to beautie, and mildenes, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and modeſtie of minde, to the welfauourednes of face and the outward feature, as I ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue in the Legend of <hi>Sara.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides her bodily chaſtitie and virginall puritie, whereof the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture beareth witnes, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſhe was a Virgin, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne of man; her induſtrie and diligence is alſo ſet downe to her praiſe: for ſhe led not an idle or laſie kinde of life, as many maides now a dayes doe, but ſhe was em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the dayly ſeruice of her fathers houſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 24.16.17.18 19.20.</note> for <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant found her drawing water at
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20087:45"/>
the well for her fathers cattell. Whereby young women and <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>27</label> maides are taught to inure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues euen from their verie ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der yeeres; to vertuous and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table employments, and not to be aſhamed to take paines about their parents houſhold affaires: conſidering how that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more contrary to chaſtitie then idlenes and lazines, which is the roote of all euill, and the mother of all miſchiefe.<note place="margin">Ezech. 16.49.</note> This may be ſeene in the Sodomites, who were full of idlenes and alſo of vnnaturall luſt: alſo in <hi>Dina Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> daughter,<note place="margin">Gen. 34.1.2.</note> who by her idle gadding abroad loſt her virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Likewiſe in <hi>Dauid,</hi> who being idle,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 11.1.2.3.4.</note> committed adulterie with the beautious <hi>Bathſheba Vriahs</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>28</label> wife.</p>
               <p>Moreouer in the perſon of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>becca,</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:20087:45"/>
women are taught to ſhew all humanity &amp; curteſie towards ſtrangers and wayfaring folkes, eſpecially thoſe of their owne ſexe. For <hi>Rebccca</hi> diſdained not to draw water for <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeruant being a ſtranger to her, and not onely for him, but alſo for his Camels; wherein likewiſe her great humilitie &amp; lowlines is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcried. She diſdained not to ſerue <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeruant, &amp; God in requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of this her lowly and humble behauiour, aduanced her to be the miſtreſſe of the man to whome ſhe had formerly behaued her ſelfe as a ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e humbled her ſelfe, and the Lord honoured her; ſhe debaſed her ſelfe, &amp; the Lord lift her vp.<note place="margin">Iam. 5.5.</note> And therefore the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtle exhorteth all perſons but chiefely the yonger ſort to humility, ſaying, <hi>Decke your ſelues
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:20087:46"/>
inwardly in lowlines of minde, for God reſiſteth the proud,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 5.11. &amp; 22.29. &amp; 40.6.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and giueth grace to the humble, he abaſeth and bringeth lowe the arrogant and proud, and lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vp the lowly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 24.49.50.51 52.57.58.</note>
                  <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeruant hauing asked <hi>Rebecca</hi> of her parents to be <hi>Iſacks</hi> wife, ſhe was graunted vnto him accordingly and ſent away home with him to <hi>Iſack</hi> with her owne conſent, and without all delay. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>29</label> Wherein we may learne how that the Lord bleſſeth and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth the affaires of ſuch as feare him, and commend their errands (as this Godly ſeruant did) vnto Gods fatherly care.<note place="margin">1. Pet 5.7.</note> Caſt all your care on him, for he careth for <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>30</label> you, ſaith the Apoſtle. Likewiſe parents heere are taught not to beſtow their children in mariage without their free conſent, the parties muſt not be hand-faſted
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:20087:46"/>
by their parents, before they be hart-faſted of their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. No violent thing laſtes long, and loue that is conſtrained cannot continue. True loue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two parties muſt flowe from the heart on both hands, and the faſtening of the heart muſt goe before the faſtning of the hand. Neither can there be any true content in this kinde, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that mutuall conſent doe goe before. And the want of this hath marred many matches, and euen turned mariages into marra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; for ſo may all conſtrained coniunction be rightly called.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rebecca</hi> being ready to depart,<note place="margin">Gen. 24.60.</note> her parents &amp; her brother bleſſed her, wiſhing that ſhe might grow into thouſand thouſands and that her ſeede might poſſeſſe the gate of their enemies. In like manner the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20087:47"/>
people that were preſent at the matrimoniall ſolemnitie of <hi>Booz</hi> and <hi>Ruth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ruth 4.11</note> prayed that the Lord would make <hi>Ruth like Rahel and Leah, which twain did build the houſe of Iſrael: and that</hi> Booz <hi>might doe worthily in Ephrathah, and be famous in Bethlehem.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>Raguel</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed yong <hi>Tobias</hi> and <hi>Sara</hi> his wife,<note place="margin">Tob. 10.11 12.</note> ſaying, <hi>The God of heauen make you my children to proſper before I die. And he ſaid to his daughter, honour thy father &amp; thy mother in law, which are now thy parents, that I may heare good report of thee, and he kiſsed them. Edna alſo ſaid to Tobias, the Lord of heauen reſtore thee my deare Brother, and grant that I may ſee thy children of my daughter Sara, that I may reioyce before the Lord. Beholde now I commit to thee my daughter as a pledge, do not <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>31</label> entreate her euill.</hi> Wherein parents and kinsfolkes are taught to pray
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20087:47"/>
vnto God to bleſſe their children and friends, being about to liue in the honorable eſtate of mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and to aduiſe them diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, touching ſuch godly duties as doe belong vnto married folkes, whether in regard of themſelues, or in regard of their houſhold.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rebecca</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming home to <hi>Iſack,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 24.64 65.</note> as ſoone as ſhe ſaw him a far off, ſhe lighted downe from her Camel, &amp; couered her head with a vaile, in token of ſhamefaſtnes, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, pudicitie, and ſubiection.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 32.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Before aſhamefaſt perſon goeth fauour,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ieſus</hi> the ſon of <hi>Sirach.</hi> And <hi>Rebecca</hi> for reward of her ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtnes, found fauour both with God and man. There is no orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ſo much becommeth a <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>32</label> maide, as the maidens bluſh, which alwayes doth bewray a ſhamefaſt diſpoſition: And ſhe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20087:48"/>
that wanteth this ſhamefaſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, lacketh a rare Iewell, and therefore <hi>Siracides</hi> aduiſeth pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to haue a diligent and a watchfull eye ouer their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in whom this ſigne of ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtnes doth not appeare. <hi>If thy daughter be not ſhamefast (ſaith he) holde her ſtraitly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 26.10 11. &amp; 42.9.10 11.</note> 
                  <hi>leaſt ſhe abuſe her ſelfe through too much libertie, leaſt ſhe cauſe thine enemies to laugh thee to ſcorne, and make thee a common talke in the Citie, and defame thee among the people, and bring thee to publicke ſhame. Take heede of her that hath an vnſhamefaſt eye, and maruaile not, if ſhe treſpaſſe againſt thee. The daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter maketh the father to watch ſecretly ſaith he, and the carefulnes that he hath for her, taketh away his ſleepe in the houſe, leaſt ſhe ſhould paſſe the flower of her age, and when ſhe hath an husband, leaſt ſhe ſhould be hated.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:20087:48"/>
In her virginitie, least ſhe ſhould be defloured in her fathers houſe, and when ſhe is in her husbands houſe, leaſt ſhe ſhould misbehaue her ſelfe, &amp; proue vnfaithfull: ſhe that is bolde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccle. 22.5</note> 
                  <hi>impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and vnſhamefaſt</hi> (ſaith the ſame wiſe man) <hi>diſhonoreth both her father and her husband, &amp; is not infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to the vngodly.</hi> Contrariwiſe, <hi>a ſhamefast, loyall, peaceable woman,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 26.14.15</note> 
                  <hi>and of good heart</hi> (that is to ſay) of an honeſt heart, for an honeſt heart, is the beſt heart in the world) <hi>is a gift of the Lord, and there is no weight to be compared to her continent minde.</hi> Such a goodly gift receiued godly <hi>Iſack</hi> at Gods hands when as he was going out to pray in the field towards the euening.<note place="margin">Gen. 24.62.67.</note> In his prayer no doubt but he asked of God amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bleſſings a vertuous wife; and God who hath ſaid to euerie
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:20087:49"/>
beleeuing ſoule, <hi>aske and it ſhall be giuen you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7 7</note> heard him and granted him his deſire.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Iſack</hi> after his prayer found a good thing, for he that find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a vertuous wife, findeth a good thing:<note place="margin">Pro 18.22</note> ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> after his prayer he receiued a gift at Gods hands and a good portion. <hi>For a vertuous and ſhamefaſt woman is a good portion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 19 14. Eccleſ. 26.14.15.24</note> 
                  <hi>which ſhall be giuen for a gift vnto ſuch as feare the Lord, ſaith Salomon</hi> and likewiſe <hi>Siraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: Iſack</hi> after pis prayer found a poſſeſſion, an heritage, an helpe, and a piller to reſt vpon. For he that hath gotten a vertuous wife, hath gotten all theſe,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 36 24. &amp; 22.4</note> 
                  <hi>and a wiſe daughter is an heritage vnto her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ieſus</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach. Iſack</hi> after his prayer, found a matter of ioy, gladnes, and long life. For he found a wife full of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:20087:49"/>
grace,<note place="margin">Eccleſ 26.1.2.17.13</note> 
                  <hi>and the grace of a wife is the thing that moſt reioyceth her husband, for ſhe feedeth his bones with her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. Bleſſed is the man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Siracides) that hath a vertuous wife, for the nomber of his yeres ſhall be dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: an honeſt woman reioyceth her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and ſhe ſhall ſee the yeeres of his life with pence.</hi> Whereas contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>an euill wife is as a yoke of Oxen that draw diuers waies, and he that hath her is as though he held a Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> For ſuch a one maketh her husbands life ſhort, for the verie talke of her tongue, is like the ſting of a Scorpions taile. <hi>Iſack</hi> after his prayer found an orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his houſe,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 26.16.</note> 
                  <hi>for as the Sunne when it ariſeth in the high places of the Lord, ſo is the beautie of a good wife the ornament of her houſe. Iſack</hi> after his prayer in his wife <hi>Rebecca,</hi> found a Crowne:<note place="margin">Prou. 12.4.</note> for <hi>a vertuous
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:20087:50"/>
woman is the Crowne of her husband,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon.</hi> Finally <hi>Iſack</hi> after prayer found an ineſtimable trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 26.14.15.</note> 
                  <hi>for there is nothing ſo much worth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ieſus</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach) as a woman well inſtructed, and no weight to be compared vnto her continent minde. Who ſhall finde a vertuous woman</hi> (ſaith king <hi>Lemuel) for her price is farre aboue the pearles. The heart of her husband truſteth in her,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 31.10 11.12.28.29.</note> 
                  <hi>and he ſhall haue no neede of ſpoile. She will doe him good and not euill all the dayes of her life: her husband alſo ſhall praiſe her, ſaying, many daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters haue done vertuouſly: but thou ſurmounteſt them all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee that godly <hi>Iſack</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his prayer, in one good wife found a treaſure of good things, and in one bleſſing receiued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>33</label> bleſſings. To teach vs that prayer is the proper meanes to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:20087:50"/>
pull downe vpon vs aboundance of Gods good things, and as <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca</hi> performed the duties of a vertuous wife in her husbands behalfe: ſo did <hi>Iſack</hi> play the part of diſcreete and louing husband towards her.<note place="margin">Gen. 24.67</note> For it is ſaid that he loued <hi>Rebecca,</hi> and was comforted in her, and by her, after his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers death: for as I ſaid before, out of <hi>Siracides, the grace of a good wife reioyceth her husband,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 26.1.2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>and doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the nomber of his dayes.</hi> And as it is recorded that he loued <hi>Rebec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> ſo is it alſo,<note place="margin">Gen. 26.8.</note> that he reioyced and ſported with her; according to that which the wiſe man inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſaying,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Reioyce with thy wife which thou haſt loued all the dayes of the life which God hath giuen thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sunne.</hi> And the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle as he enioyneth wiues to be of holy behauiour, ſober, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:20087:51"/>
diſcreete,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.2.3.4.5 Colloſſ 18 19 Epheſ. 5.25 28.</note> chaſt, keeping at home ſubiect, louers of their husbands and of their children; ſo likewiſe he exhorteth husbands to loue their wiues, as their owne bodyes, and not to be bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>34</label> vnto them, <hi>for he that loueth his wife</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>loueth himſelfe.</hi> If a mans wife be of a ſweet and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious diſpoſition; then ought the husband to ioyne his ſweetnes to his wiues, except he meane to ſhew himſelfe a beaſt, yea worſe then a beaſt, in being bitter and ſowre in the behalfe of his vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wife. And if otherwiſe ſhe be of a more bitter &amp; vnpleaſing diſpoſition then behooueth, then he muſt ſhew himſelfe wiſe in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying the ſowreneſſe and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his wines behauiour, with the ſweeteneſſe of his patient and gentle inclination: in labouring
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:20087:51"/>
to reclaime her by all kinde of faire perſwaſions, and enduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of loue. Thus the diſcreete husband may amend that male-pleaſing humour of his wife; whereas by vſing bitternes in her behalfe, he ſhall turne his wiues wormwood into gall of aſpes, and make her ten folde more bitter and ſowre then ſhe was at firſt.</p>
               <p>Thus then in the perſon of <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>35</label> godly <hi>Iſack</hi> and vertuous <hi>Rebecca,</hi> are all huſbands and wiues taught to labour by all meanes to be a comfort, and ioy one vnto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Wiues to loue in moſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire manner their husbands, to reuerence and obey them with all ſubiection &amp; ſubmiſſion of body and minde, and to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a matter of ioy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto them: and husbands on the other part, to make much of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:20087:52"/>
their wiues, to loue them entier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and to eſteeme of them as their greateſt ornament, their beſt por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, their deareſt inheritance, their ſureſt helpe, their ſtrongeſt piller, their ſweeteſt comfort, their richeſt pearle, and in one worde, as their moſt glorious crowne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 25.21 &amp; 24.63.64.</note>
                  <hi>Rebecca</hi> was barren for a time, but the Lord at the prayer and entreatie of her husband <hi>Iſack</hi> made her to beare. Thus <hi>Iſack</hi> as by prayer he had obtained a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous wife, ſo by prayer he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed at Gods hands, for his wife, the ſtrength and ability to <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>36</label> conceiue, and to beare children. Wherein, we finde that ſaying of the Apoſtle verified.<note place="margin">Iam. 5.16.</note> 
                  <hi>The prayer of a righteous man availeth much if it be feruent.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 20 17 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> was a righteous man, and at his prayer <hi>Abimelechs</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:20087:52"/>
wife ceaſed to be barren, and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech</hi> himſelfe was healed:<note place="margin">Deut. 9.20 21. Num. 12.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> was a righteous man, and at his prayer <hi>Aron</hi> purchaſed pardon for his idolatrie, and <hi>Miriam</hi> was cured of her leaprie:<note place="margin">Num. 16.47.48.</note> 
                  <hi>Aron</hi> was a righteous man, and at his prayer the plague ceaſed from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. <hi>Samuel</hi> was a righteous man,<note place="margin">1. Sam 7.8 9.10.11.12</note> and at his prayer the Iſralites ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred &amp; ouercame the Philiſtims. <hi>Eliah</hi> was a righteous man,<note place="margin">1. King. 17 17.18.19 20.21.22.23. &amp; 18.45.</note> and at his prayer he obtained raine after the drought of three yeeres, and reſtored his hoſteſſe ſonne to life. Likewiſe at his prayer the two captaines ouer fifty with their fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſent by <hi>Ahaziah</hi> to apprehend him,<note place="margin">2. King. 1.7.8.9.10 11.12.13.</note> were deuoured by fire from heauen, and the third captaine with his fiftie at the Prophets de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire were preſerued. <hi>Eliſha</hi> was a righteous man, and at his prayer,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:20087:53"/>
the Shunamite conceiued &amp; bare a ſonne to her husband being old,<note place="margin">2. King. 4.12.13.14 15.16.17 31.33.34 35.36.</note> and that after long barrennes, whome afterwards he alſo reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe to life being dead: likewiſe at his prayer, the men that the king of Sirya had ſent to apprehend him,<note place="margin">2 King. 18 &amp; 2.23.24.</note> was ſmitten with blindnes. And the 42. children that mocked him, were torne in peeces by two Beares out of the Forreſt. The Prophet ſent by God to <hi>Ieroboam</hi> to reproue him, was a righteous man, and at his prayer <hi>Ieroboams</hi> hand being firſt dried vp was reſtored:<note place="margin">1. King. 13 6</note> So great is the force of a righteous mans prayer. It openeth the windowes of heauen to giue raine after long drineſſe, and the wombe of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to beare after long barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. As the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>through God I am able to doe all
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:20087:53"/>
things:</hi> So through prayer is the righteous man able to obtaine all things.</p>
               <p>And as <hi>Iſack</hi> had his recourſe vnto God by prayer,<note place="margin">Gen. 25.22.23.28.</note> to make his wife fruitfull; ſo She hauing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and feeling the children in her wombe to ſtriue together, it is ſaid that ſhe went to aske the Lord concerning the meaning of <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>37</label> that matter. Wherein men and women are taught in euerie diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie to haue their recourſe vnto God by prayer, for this hath been alwayes the cuſtome of Gods people both women and men. It was reuealed vnto her that the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhould ſerue the yonger, and that <hi>Iacob</hi> ſhould be more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto God then <hi>Eſau,</hi> and therefore the holy woman loued <hi>Iacob</hi> more then <hi>Eſau:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 27.6.10</note> and by her counſaile and prudence, he got
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:20087:54"/>
the bleſſing from his brother <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau;</hi> for whome the Lord bleſſeth and loueth, ſhall be bleſſed and loued of the beſt men likewiſe. And when as <hi>Eſau</hi> in reuenge had intended to ſlay <hi>Iacob, Rebecca</hi> (which by interpretation is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as contention hindered) did indeede and in effect anſwere vnto her name: and therefore to <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>38</label> hinder this mortall and bloudy ſtrife betweene her two children, ſhe ſent <hi>Iacob</hi> away to <hi>Haran</hi> to her Brother <hi>Laban</hi> there to tarrie vntill <hi>Eſaus</hi> fiercenes were aſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.<note place="margin">Gen. 27.41 42.43.44.45.</note> In which doing, <hi>Rebecca</hi> as ſhe bewraied both her wiſdome and her peaceable diſpoſition, So hath ſhe left vnto all women, wiues, and mothers, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of imitation to preſerue peace, and to preuent ſtrife and contention amongſt her children
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:20087:54"/>
and ſeruants. Happie then was godly <hi>Iſack</hi> to haue receiued at the Lords hands ſuch a vertuous wife and peaceable wife as was <hi>Rebecca, for a peaceable woman and of gaod feare</hi> (ſaith <hi>Siracides) is a gift of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 26.1.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and there is nothing ſo much worth as a woman that is well inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and bleſsed is the man that hath a vertuous wife</hi> ſaith the ſame wiſe man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:20087:55"/>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:20087:55"/>
               <head>The golden Legend of IACOB and RAHEL.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>ACOB</hi> whome the Lord loued eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was borne,<note place="margin">Malach. 1.2 Rom 9.13. Gen. 25.21 22.23.28.</note> and of whome he had foretolde that his elder brother ſhould ſerue him, was borne of <hi>Rebekah,</hi> after that God at the requeſt of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <hi>Iſack</hi> had taken away her barrenneſſe. As God loued him before he was borne, ſo his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loued him more then her el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſonne <hi>Eſau</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was borne.
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:20087:56"/>
So that by Gods prouidence who loued him, and the counſaile of his mother who tendred him, he obteyned of his father the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing which by the law of birth was due vnto <hi>Eſau</hi> as being the elder. <hi>God giue thee of the dewe of Heauen and the fatnes of the earth and plentie of wheate and wine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 27.6.7.8.9.23.28.29.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.37</note> (ſaid <hi>Iſack</hi> in bleſſing of his ſonne) <hi>let people be thy ſeruants and nations bow vnto thee: curſed be he that curſeth thee and bleſſed be he that bleſſeth thee.</hi> So that when as <hi>Eſau</hi> did complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly expoſtulate in the preſence of his father, againſt his brother, <hi>Iſacks</hi> anſwere was, <hi>I haue bleſſed thy brother, therfore he ſhall be bleſsed: behold I haue made him thy Lord, and <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>39</label> all his brethren haue I made his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.</hi> Wherein we may learne firſt, whoſoeuer is beloued and bleſſed of God as <hi>Iacob</hi> was, ſhall
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:20087:56"/>
alſo be beloued and bleſſed of all godly men and women, ſuch as <hi>Iſack</hi> and <hi>Rebekah</hi> were. And next that, ſuch as honour the Lord, and ſerue him as <hi>Iacob</hi> did, the Lord will honour them with <hi>Iacob</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>40</label> and euen make others to ſerue them, as he made <hi>Eſau</hi> to ſerue his younger brother <hi>Iaccob,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that ſaying vttered by the Lords owne mouth.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.30.</note> 
                  <hi>Them that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour me, will I honour, and them that deſpiſe me ſhall be deſpiſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> got his fathers bleſſing in his elder brothers clothes;<note place="margin">Gen. 27.15 16.</note> and we chriſtians which be <hi>Iacobs</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>41</label> according to the promiſe, muſt get our heauenly fathers bleſſing in our elder brothers coate, that is to ſay, being cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with the wedding garment of Chriſts righteouſnes:<note place="margin">Mat. 22.11 Gen. 25.27</note> 
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> was a plaine man, that is, he was harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:20087:57"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>42</label> and innocent: And chriſtians are enioyned to be harmeles as Lambes,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.16</note> and innocent as Doues. <hi>Iacob</hi> to ſhunne and eſhew the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and fierceneſſe of his brother <hi>Eſau</hi> fled from his fathers houſe in <hi>Beerſheba,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 27.43.44.45 &amp; 28.10.</note> to <hi>Haran</hi> to his Vncle <hi>Laban</hi> the brother of <hi>Rebecca.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>43</label> And our Sauiour Chriſt enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his Apoſtles, and in their perſons all chriſtians, to flee from the furie of their perſecuters. <hi>When they perſecute you in this Citie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 10.16.23,</note> ſaith he, <hi>then flee into another.</hi> Chriſtians muſt carrie themſelues towards their perſecuters, as ſheep in the midſt of Wolues; their ſureſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſtandeth in flight: for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing becommeth chriſtians bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then patience and ſuffrance of wronges. And it is the moſt eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall propertie of a true chriſtian not to offer, but to ſuffer iniuries.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:20087:57"/>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> being in his iourney, came vnto a certaine place,<note place="margin">Gen 28.11.12.</note> and taried there all night, and tooke of the ſtones of the place, and layed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his head, and ſlept. Young <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> had but a verie vneaſie lying, when as he layed his head vpon the hard ſtones.<note place="margin">Gen. 28.20.21.22 &amp; 32.10.</note> He went out onely with a poore ſtaffe in his hand, and begged of God but bread to eate, and cloathes to put on together with preſeruation and ſafetie in his iourney, going and returning home againe. Whereby chriſtians are taught <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>44</label> to commend their voyages, and wayes vnto Gods prouidence, &amp; to be content with ſuch things as are neceſſarie for the conſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life, as alſo to avoid luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, voluptuouſnes and ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; and to inure themſelues to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure indigence, ſcarcitie and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurie,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:20087:58"/>
till at what time God opens his hand, in a more libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall manner for our reliefe. <hi>Iacobs</hi> greateſt deſire vnto the Lord, was that he would be with him, and ſo he was according to his wiſh. And euen the ſame night that he did lye ſo lowe and ſo hard, the Lord with his holy Angells came as it were to ſee his ſeruant lying on the ground,<note place="margin">Gen. 28.12.13.14 15.</note> with his head v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the hard ſtones. <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaw in his ſleepe a ladder ſtanding vpon the earth, and the top of it reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp to heauen. And loe the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God went vp &amp; downe by it, &amp; the Lord ſtood aboue it, and promiſed to giue him the land v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the which he then lay, euen to him and to his ſeede; the which ſhould be as the duſt of the ground, and be ſpread abroade e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the foure corners of the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:20087:58"/>
earth. Moreouer, that he would be with him, and keepe him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſoeuer he ſhould goe, yea &amp; bring him againe into that land, and neuer forſake him vntill his whole promiſes were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
               <p>Whereby we are taught that <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>45</label> alwayes at the greateſt pinch of Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, God is moſt preſent, And when they are as it were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken and abandoned of all, that euen then the Lord is moſt neere vnto them, to miniſter vnto them comfort, aſſiſtance and aide.<note place="margin">Gen 21.16</note> 
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> being awake out of his dreame, ſaid, <hi>Surely the Lord is in this place and I was not aware.</hi> And ſo the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man may ſay, when as in his greateſt exigents and extremities, he findeth and feeleth Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence for his good: ſurely the Lord hath beene with me,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:20087:59"/>
though not in a viſible manner. <hi>Iacob</hi> had vnder his head hard ſtones, but aboue his head was God ſtanding, and the Angels walking vp and downe by a Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Whereby we are let to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>46</label> that if with <hi>Iacob</hi> we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome aduerſitie, and the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; harſhnes of affliction heere below, by the meanes of a chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an courage, that in end we ſhall be rewarded with the ſocietie of God &amp; his Angels aboue. <hi>Take my brethren</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Iames) the Prophets for an enſmple of ſuffering aduerſitie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 5.10.11</note> 
                  <hi>and of long patience, which haue ſpoken in the name of the Lord: Beholde we count them bleſſed which endure. It is thankes worthie</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Peter) if a man for conſcience toward God endure griefe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.19 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.21. &amp; 4.13</note> 
                  <hi>ſuffering wrongfully, for Chriſt alſo ſuffered for vs, leaning vs an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample that we ſhould follow his ſteps:
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:20087:59"/>
wherefore reioyce, in as much as ye are partakers of Chriſts ſuffrings, that when his glorie ſhall appeare, ye may be glad and reioyce.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs run with patience</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) the race that is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, looking vnto Ieſus the authour and finiſher of our faith, who for the ioy that was ſet before him, endured the Croſſe, and deſpiſed the ſhame, and is ſet at the right hand of the throne of God.</hi> Hence it is, that we alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in tribulations,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.3.4.5.</note> knowing that <hi>tribulation bringeth forth pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and patience experience, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hope,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.12</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; hope maketh not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: for if we ſuffer with Chriſt, we ſhall alſo raigne with him:</hi> If we beare the Croſſe heere with him on earth, we ſhall alſo weare a crowne hereafter with him in heauen. <hi>Iacob</hi> lying vpon the ſtones, found notwithſtanding reſt to his Body: and if we repoſe
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:20087:60"/>
our ſelues wholy vpon the Rock,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.4. Gen. 49.24. Dan. 2.34.41</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> whome <hi>Iacob</hi> calleth the ſtone of Iſrael; and <hi>Daniel,</hi> the the ſtone cut without hands; we ſhall not faile to finde reſt to our ſoules. And Chriſt ſhall be vnto <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>47</label> vs not onely a Rock to reſt vpon and a ſtone to ſtay vpon, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a Ladder to climbe vpon, wherby we may aſcend from this earth wherein is all hardnes, vnto the kingdome of heauen where is all happines.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> being come vnto his Vncle <hi>Labans</hi> houſe, entered into ſeruice with <hi>Laban,</hi> in which his ſeruice he was ſo exceedingly bleſſed of God,<note place="margin">Gen. 30.27.43.</note> that he became very rich, &amp; got many flocks, maidſeruants, and men ſeruants, Camels and Aſſes. Moreouer <hi>Laban</hi> confeſſed that the Lord had bleſſed and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched him likwiſe for <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſake.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:20087:60"/>
Whereby the children of <hi>Iacob</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>48</label> are taught not to liue Idlely and without ſome lawfull calling or trade, and rather to embrace the condition of ſeruice then to ſpend their time in ſluggiſhnes, idlenes, and ſinne. And therefore we read that <hi>Iacob</hi> brought vp his owne children in the occupation of ſheepe-heardes.<note place="margin">Gen. 46.34. &amp; 47.3</note> And <hi>Saul</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from ſeeking of his fathers Aſſes,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 9.3 &amp; 16.11.12.19</note> and <hi>Dauid</hi> from keeping of his fathers ſheepe, to feede and rule the people of Iſrael: and the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> as he wrought with his owne hands,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.7 8.9.10 11 Act. 20.34</note> ſo he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth that the man that will not worke, ſhould not eate. And therefore he exhorteth idle men to worke with quietnes, and to eate their owne bread, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, recommendeth vnto them his owne example for imitation, how
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:20087:61"/>
that he tooke not bread of any man for nought, but wrought with labour and trauaile, night and day, becauſe he would not be chargeable to any of them.<note place="margin">Pro. 5.15. &amp; 12.11 14 &amp; 14.23. &amp; 20.4. &amp; 21.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Drinke the water of thy Ciſterne and of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers out of the midſt of thine owne well</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon:</hi> inſinuating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, how that men ought to liue of their owne laboures. <hi>He that tilleth his land ſhal be ſatiſfied with bread, but he that followeth the idle, is deſtitute of vnderſtanding: the recompence of a mans h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>as ſhall God giue vnto him, and in all labour there is aboundance. The ſlothfull will not plowgh, becauſe of winter, therefore ſhall he begge in ſummer but haue nothing: he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth paſtime ſhall he a poore man, and he that loueth Wine and Oyle, ſhall not be rich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> then who was ſo excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding rich, was no doubt verie free
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:20087:61"/>
from the vices of idlenes, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie and exceſſe, And yet it was <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>49</label> not ſo much his labour as the bleſſing of the Lord that made him rich.<note place="margin">Pſal. 1 27.1.2</note> 
                  <hi>Except the Lord builde the houſe</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>they labour in vaine that build it; except the Lord keepe the Citie, the keeper watcheth in vaine. It is vaine for you to riſe early, &amp; to lie down late, &amp; to eate the bread of ſorrow, but he will ſurely giue rest to his beloued.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, it is in vaine for a man to toyle and moyle day and night, except the Lord bleſſe his buſines as he did <hi>Iacobs,</hi> &amp; <hi>Labans</hi> likewiſe for <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſake, and as he did <hi>Ioſephes</hi> affaires and his three maiſters for <hi>Ioſephes</hi> ſake, firſt in <hi>Potiphars</hi> houſe,<note place="margin">Gen 39. &amp; 40. &amp; 41</note> then in the priſon, &amp; laſtly in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Pallace. <hi>Iacob</hi> ſerued twiſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeeres, his Vncle <hi>Laban</hi> for his daughter <hi>Rahel:</hi> For it is ſaid that
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:20087:62"/>
he loued her and euen ſo earneſtly and feruently,<note place="margin">Gen. 20.18 28.30.</note> that ſo many yeeres did ſeeme vnto him but a fewe dayes. Wherby ſuch as are about <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>50</label> mariag are taught to make choiſe onely of ſuch parties as they can moſt entierly loue.<note place="margin">Gen. 25.23 25.26.27.28</note> As <hi>Iacob</hi> being the yonger of <hi>Iſacks</hi> two ſonnes was more beloued of God, and of his mother <hi>Rebecca</hi> then the elder ſonne <hi>Eſau:</hi> So of <hi>Labans</hi> two daughters being <hi>Iacobs</hi> two wiues, the younger was more loued of <hi>Iacob</hi> then the elder,<note place="margin">Gen. 29.16 17.18.19.20.</note> euen faire <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hel</hi> more then tender-eyed <hi>Leah.</hi> As of the two brethren the Lord made choyſe of the younger;<note place="margin">Mat. 1.2. Rom 9.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Iacob haue I loued:</hi> ſo of the two ſiſters, <hi>Iacob</hi> made choiſe of the younger, for <hi>Rahel</hi> he loued &amp; ſerued twice ſeauen yeares for her.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid of <hi>Rahel</hi> that ſhe was beautifull and faire; the ſame is
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:20087:62"/>
ſaid of <hi>Sara,</hi> and of <hi>Rebecca,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.3.</note> and likewiſe of <hi>Abigail</hi> who was both beautifull and ſingularly wiſe. <hi>Abigail</hi> is aſmuch by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation as fathers ioy; and ſuch a one was <hi>Rahel,</hi> euen the ioy of her father <hi>Laban,</hi> and likewiſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> her louing husband,<note place="margin">Pro. 10.1. Eccleſ. 26.1.2.13.</note> for as <hi>a wiſe daughter is the ioy of her father,</hi> ſo is <hi>a wiſe wife the ioy of her husband</hi> ſaith the wiſe man. And <hi>Rahel La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans</hi> daughter, and <hi>Iacobs</hi> wife <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gail,</hi> like was both. The greateſt glorie of a daughter is to be called her fathers or her mothers ioy; And the greateſt glorie of a wife is to be accounted the ioy of her husband. And heere all daughters <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>51</label> and wiues are taught to endeuour by all meanes to be ſuch as <hi>Rahel</hi> and <hi>Abigail</hi> were. <hi>Iacob</hi> loued <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hel</hi> for her beautie, but yet more for her bountie and gracious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:20087:63"/>
                  <hi>For fauour is deceitfull,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 31.30.</note> 
                  <hi>and beauty is euaniſhings, but a woman that feareth the Lord, ſhe ſhall be praiſed</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> &amp; ſuch a one was <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hel,</hi> who was not ſo faire in body as ſhe was in minde, &amp; therefore worthie to be loued of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and landed of men. <hi>The beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a woman cheereth the face</hi> (ſaith <hi>Siracides) and a man loueth nothing better,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 36.22.23.24</note> 
                  <hi>if there be in her tongue gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, meeknes, and wholſome talke, then is not her husband like other men.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>52</label> The beautie of a woman indeede cheereth the face, but the bounty of a woman cheereth the minde more, and is the ſweeteſt ſolace of the ſoule. The eye of man loueth nothing better then beautie, and the heart of man loueth nothing better then bountie: the beautie of a wel-behaued woman is in the houſe,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 26.16 17 18.</note> as the candle light in the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:20087:63"/>
Temple,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 22.4 &amp; 36.24</note> or the Sunne-light in the heauen, ſaith <hi>Siracides.</hi> But the wiſdome of a woman is the heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and heartes-caſe of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. The beautie of a wife is the ornament of her houſe; but the bountie and wiſdome of a wife buildeth the houſe.<note place="margin">Prou. 14.1</note> 
                  <hi>for a wiſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> (ſaith the wiſe man) <hi>buildeth the houſe, but the fooliſh deſtroyeth it with her owne hands.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 31.10.16.26.</note> And king <hi>Lemuels</hi> vertuous woman as ſhe openeth her mouth with wiſdome, &amp; hath the law of grace in her tongue, ſo ſhe conſidereth a field and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it, and with the fruite of her hands ſhe planteth a vinyard.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe it is recorded of <hi>Rahel</hi> and <hi>Leah</hi> that they twaine builded the houſe of Iſrael:<note place="margin">Ruth 4.11</note> 
                  <hi>Rahel</hi> then did not eate the bread of idlenes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther when ſhe was maried, nor yet when ſhe was a maide: ſhe was
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:20087:64"/>
not like thoſe careles women de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the Prophet <hi>Iſay,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 32.9.10.11.12 13.14. Pro. 31.10. to 31.</note> but rather like the vertuous woman deſcribed by <hi>Salomon.</hi> Being mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhe did take paines, in ouerſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the worke of her ſeruants, and diſdained not to worke cheerfully with her hands: and being a maid, ſhe was employed in keeping of her fathers ſheepe, leauing an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>53</label> to all matrons and maides to flie idlenes. As her calling was to keepe ſheepe, ſo her name ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth a ſheepe: ſo that her verie name ſerued to put her in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of her calling. But chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſhew her how that ſhe ſhould endeuour to be like vnto the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>54</label> ſheepe in innocencie and harmles ſimplicitie: and therefore our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth compare often his followers to ſheepe. Vnto his Diſciples he ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.16.</note> 
                  <hi>beholde I ſend
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:20087:64"/>
you as Sheepe in the midſt of Wolues: be ye therefore wiſe as Serpents, and innocent as Doues.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh 10.1.2.3.4 11 14.15.</note> And of al his elect children, he ſaith that his ſheepe heare his voice, and that he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them by their name, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them out, and goeth before them, and that they follow him, and know his voice, and that he himſelfe is the good ſhepheard that giueth his life for his ſheep.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rahel</hi> and <hi>Leah, Iacobs</hi> two wiues were barren for a time, but it is ſaid that in end God remembred and heard them: God may ſeeme for a time to forget his children, and not to heare them, but in end they may be ſure to be both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred and heard. Not that God doth at any time forget his <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>55</label> children indeede, and not heare their requeſts; but that ſomtimes he doth carie himſelfe to our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion
<pb facs="tcp:20087:65"/>
and feeling, as one that is ſubiect to forgetfulnes, and not willing to heare what we ſay or ſue for at his hands, and that he doth euen for our good: for ſo it pleaſeth him to exerciſe vs and to ſtirre vs vp to greater feruencie and earneſtnes in prayer. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the delay of a benifite, ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſame, when it is obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. That good thing which hath beene gotten with great difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, with much adoe, and after long delay, is by many degrees more deare vnto vs, then if it had beene gotten with eaſe and at an inſtant.<note place="margin">Gen. 29.31.32. &amp; 30.17.22.</note> The Lord at laſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred &amp; heard <hi>Rahel &amp; Leah</hi> which did both of them begge children at his hands: For it is the Lord that openeth the windowes of heauen (being ſhut) to giue raine,<note place="margin">1. King. 18 1.41.45.</note> to make the earth fruitfull: and it
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:20087:65"/>
is likewiſe the Lord that openeth the barren womans wombe to make her the ioyfull mother of many children,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.5 Pſal. 113.9 &amp; 128.3.</note> ſo that ſhe is made as the fruitfull vine on the houſe ſides, and her children ſtand like O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue plants round about the Table.</p>
               <p>And as it is ſaid that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred <hi>Rahel</hi> and <hi>Leah</hi> when he deliuered them from barrennes, ſo is it alſo ſaid that he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred <hi>Noah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 8.1.</note> when as he made the waters to ceaſe vpon the earth, &amp; he remembred <hi>Abraham</hi> when as he deliuered <hi>Lot</hi> at <hi>Abrahams</hi> requeſt,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.29</note> from the deſtruction of <hi>Sodome:</hi> and he remembred <hi>Iſmael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 21.17</note> when as he deliuered him from extremitie of indigence, and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed him in the wildernes, being caſt out together with his mother <hi>Hagar</hi> out of <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe. And he remembred <hi>Iacob</hi> being in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation<note place="margin">Gen. 35.3.</note>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:20087:66"/>
by reaſon of his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> and deliuered him from his hoſtilitie and feare. Laſtly, thus he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred <hi>Anna</hi> when he deliuered her from barrennes,<note place="margin">1. Sam 1 11.19. Iob 14.13 &amp; 42.10.11.12.</note> and made her to beare. So we ſee that the Lords remembrance is alwayes conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with deliuerance from ſome <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>56</label> euill. Yea, not only doth God when he remembreth, deliuer from ſome euill, but he alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth ſome good: as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by theſe foreſaid examples, and by the example of <hi>Iob.</hi> So that whoſoeuer he be that ſerueth God, and ſueth vnto him, he may aſſure himſelfe, at firſt or laſt to be heard, and not to begotten for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Princes may ſometimes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get their ſeruants and ſuiters; but God neuer forgeteth his,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 22. &amp; 25. &amp; 27.2.8.9.10.11. &amp; 28 6.7. &amp; 30.10 11 &amp; 31.12.14.16.21.22.23.24 &amp; 32.6.7.10 11 &amp; 33.18 19.20 21. &amp; 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.4.5.6.15.17.18.19. &amp; 37.6.7.34. &amp; 40.1.2.16, 17.</note> onely it behooueth vs with godly <hi>Dauid</hi> to waite patiently vpon the Lord,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:20087:66"/>
and to hope in him: &amp; though for a time we ſeeme to be forgotten with <hi>Dauid</hi> as a dead man out of minde, yet we ſhall finde by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience with <hi>Dauid,</hi> that the eyes of the Lord are vpon the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and his eares open vnto their crye: That he is neere vnto them, that are of a contrite heart, and will ſaue ſuch as be afflicted in ſpirite; And that though he hide his face from vs for a while, ſo that we ſay in our haſt, loe we are caſt out of his ſight; yet ere it be long he will turne our mourning into ioy; Looſe our ſacke, and gird vs with gladnes; heare the voice of our petition, and ſhew vs his maruailous kindenes; deliuer vs from our troubles, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe vs with his mercie; eſtabliſh our hearts,<note place="margin">Iob. 8.21.</note> and fill them with his good things,<note place="margin">Pſal 27.10.</note> with gladnes and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:20087:67"/>
ioy. For though our fathers and our mothers ſhould forſake vs, and forget vs, yet the Lord will gather vs vp, ſaith the Pſalmiſt.</p>
               <p>O how much better is it then, to truſt in the Lord, rather then in Princes, or yet in our naturall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents! Let eche one ſay then with <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 130.5.6.7.8.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue waited on the Lord, my ſoule hath waited, and I haue tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in his word: my ſoule waitch on the Lord more then the morning watch watcheth for the morning. Let Iſrael waite on the Lord: for with the Lord is mercie, and with him is great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 118.8 9.</note> As it is better to truſt in God, then in Princes, ſo is it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to waite on God, then on Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For want who will, Gods waiter ſhall be ſure not to want his rewardes.<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.34</note> 
                  <hi>Waite thou on the Lord and keepe his way, and he ſhall exalt thee, and thou ſhalt inherite the land,</hi>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:20087:67"/>
ſaith that good waiter on God, godly <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 78.70 71.72.</note> who waited ſo well on God that of a fillie ſhepheard he was made a mighty monarch, and a glorious king. So that he had good cauſe to ſay, it is good for me to drawe neere to God to truſt in him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.20 &amp; 40.1. &amp; 73.28.</note> and to waite patiently on him. A king is able to make his waiter, of a meane man, a mightie man; of a Lad he is able to make him a Lord: but God can eaſily if he pleaſe, make his waiter, of a contemptible caſt-away,<note place="margin">Pſal. 113.7.8. Eccleſ. 11.1.</note> a puiſſant Prince &amp; a crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned king. <hi>It is he that raiſeth the needie out of the dust, and lifteth vp the poore out of the dung, That he may ſet him with the Princes, euen with the Princes of his people.</hi> Yea, not onely ſetteth he ſuch as waite on him, with the princes, but alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſetteth a crowne vpon their
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:20087:68"/>
heads,<note place="margin">Iob. 36 7.</note> and maketh them Princes; not onely doth he place the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous with kings in the throne, but alſo maketh them ſometimes kings,<note place="margin">Eccle. 4.14</note> and (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh) bringeth them out of the verie priſon to raigne. And therefore godly <hi>Dauid</hi> acknowledgeth that God did preuent him with liberal bleſſings,<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.3</note> and that he ſet a crowne of pure gold vpon his head. So then, as I ſaid before, be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten who will, the man that feareth God and waiteth on him ſhall not be forgotten, but ſhall be b th re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred and remunerated with an ample reward, greater then any mortall king can giue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rahel</hi> and <hi>Leah</hi> as in their bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennes they prayd vnto God for to giue them the abilitie to beare children; ſo hauing receaued at Gods hands the thing they did
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:20087:68"/>
aske, they praiſed him for the ſame. <hi>Now will I praiſe the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 29.33 35</note> 
                  <hi>ſaid Leah</hi> when ſhe had borne <hi>Iudah:</hi> &amp; <hi>Rahel</hi> hauing borne <hi>Ioſeph</hi> reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cingly praiſed the Lord for taking away her rebuke.<note place="margin">Gen. 30.23</note> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.1 to 11.</note> So the holy wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Anna</hi> hauing receiued a ſon of the Lord, praiſed him in a ſong. The like did religious <hi>Zacharie</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receiued a Sonne by his wife <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in her barren olde age.<note place="margin">Luk. 1.68. to 80.</note> Whereby both women and men <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>57</label> are taught to pray vnto God for all good things, they ſtand in need of, &amp; hauing receiued that which they did aske, to proue thankfull by praiſing him for the ſame: for the man that is not thankfull, for good things already receiued, is not worthy to receiue any more good at Gods hand. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle exhorteth chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to <hi>giue thankes alwaies for all<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.4.20.</note>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:20087:69"/>
things vnto God, euen the father, in the name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Moſes</hi> warneth the people that they doe not forget to bleſſe the Lord for their habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and foode,<note place="margin">Dent. 8.10 11.12.13 14.15.16.17.18.</note> &amp; for the increaſe of their flockes, and of their ſiluer and golde. <hi>Remember the Lord your God ſaith he, for it is he which giueth you power to get ſubſtance.</hi> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let euerie one that hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued any good thing at the Lords hand, or yet looketh to receiue more, ſay with holy <hi>Dauid; What ſhall I render vnto the Lord for all his benifites to me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.12.13.14.</note> 
                  <hi>I will take the cup of ſaluation, and call vpon the name of the Lord. I will pay my vowes vnto the Lord euen now in the preſence of all his people.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 103.1 2.3.4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>My ſoule praiſe thou the Lord, and all that is within me, praiſe his holy name. My ſoule praiſe thou the Lord, and forget not all his benefites,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:20087:69"/>
Which forgiueth all thine iniquitie, and healeth all thine infirmities; which redeemeth thy life from the graue, and crowneth thee with mercie and compaſſion; which ſatiſfieth thy youth with good things, and thy youth is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued like the Eagles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to returne from <hi>Iacobs</hi> wiues vnto himſelfe, <hi>Iacob was</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uied of his owne Couſins, <hi>Labans</hi> children, which did murmure mightily againſt him for his great wealth. Yea, <hi>Labans</hi> owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance began to be changed, ſo that he was leſſe kinde vnto him, then he had beene before.</p>
               <p>It was no doubt an affliction, and that a bitter one too, for him to be enuied of his owne neere Couſins and allies, yea of his own Vncle and father in lawe <hi>Laban,</hi> and that his good &amp; long ſeruices were not better conſidered vpon
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:20087:70"/>
by him and his children, and how that the Lord had for his ſake proſpered them all. But though his neareſt kinſ-men and allies, were thus changed in their affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards <hi>Iacob,</hi> yet in the mean time, God who is vnchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in his loue (for whom he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth,<note place="margin">Ierim. 31.3 Ioh. 13.1.</note> he loueth with an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting loue) did neuer alter his countenance and affection in his behalfe. When <hi>Iacob</hi> was moſt croſſed of men, then did God ſhew himſelfe moſt kinde. And the frowardnes of his friends was not of ſo great force to caſt him downe, as the preſent fauour of God was to holde him vp. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>58</label> Whereby we are taught to haue alwayes our greateſt affiance in Gods fauour, for though our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and our mothers, let alone our kinſ-men or allies, ſhould
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:20087:70"/>
faile vs and forſake vs;<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.10 &amp; 125.1. &amp; 146.3</note> yet the Lord will gather vs vp. <hi>They that trust in the Lord ſhall be as mount Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which cannot be remoued, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth for euer. Put not your trust in Princes</hi> (ſaith that godly Prince) <hi>nor in the ſonne of man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 17.5.6.7.8.</note> 
                  <hi>for there is no helpe in him. Curſed be the man</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his arme, and withdraweth his heart from the Lord, for he ſhall be like the heath in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, and ſhall not ſee when any good commeth, but ſhall inhabit the parched places in the Wildernes, in a ſalt land &amp; not inhabited. But bleſſed be the man that truſteth in the Lord, &amp; whoſe hope the Lord is, for he ſhall be as a tree planted by the water, which ſpreadeth out her rootes by the riuer, and ſhall not feele when the heate commeth, but her leafe ſhall be greene, and ſhall not care for the yeere of drought, neither
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:20087:71"/>
ſhall ceaſe from yeelding fruit.</hi> Such a well rooted, greene, and faire branched tree was <hi>Iacob,</hi> who tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the Lord and not in man, and therefore when as man frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on him God fauoured him,<note place="margin">Gen 31.3.13.17.18 24.</note> &amp; bid him leaue his Vncle <hi>Laban</hi> and returne into his own land: Where he pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iſed to eſtabliſh him &amp; his ſeede, &amp; to make them in number as the duſt of the earth, and as the ſtars of the heauen. And ſuch was the care of the Lord for his ſeruant <hi>Iacob</hi> that when as after his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he was purſued by his father in lawe <hi>Laban,</hi> God did admoniſh him by a dreame that he ſhould <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>59</label> not ſpeake vnto <hi>Iacob</hi> ſo much as one euill word. Wherin all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full folkes are inſtructed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and commend their wayes and eſtate vnto the gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God, who will both
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:20087:71"/>
help vs himſelfe, and hinder o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from doing vs any harme.</p>
               <p>Moreouer when as <hi>Iacob</hi> was in his iourney,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.1.2.3.4.5.6.7.</note> and was greatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted and troubled, becauſe of his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> the Lord ſent his Angels to meete him, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie him for his preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſafetie: accordirg to the ſaying of the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.7. &amp; 19.11.</note> 
                  <hi>The Angell of the Lord pitcheth round about all them that feare him, and deliuereth them. He ſhall giue his Angels charge ouer them to keepe them in all their wayes.</hi> Thus we read that the Lord comforted <hi>Hagar</hi> by an Angel,<note place="margin">Gen. 16.7. to 15</note> when ſhe fled from her miſtris <hi>Sara,</hi> for vſing her roughly. Thus an Angel ſtayed <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> at the Lords appointment,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.11.12.</note> from ſacrificing his Sonne. Thus an Angel conducted <hi>Eliezer Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> ſeruant to finde a wife for<note place="margin">Gen. 24.7.12.27.40</note>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:20087:72"/>
                  <hi>Iſack.</hi> Thus an Angell comforted <hi>Eliah</hi> and nouriſhed him when as he fled from <hi>Iezebell.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 19 5 6.7.</note> Thus an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell comforted and encouraged <hi>Ioſhua</hi> being about the beſieging of <hi>Ierico.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſh. 5.13.14.15.</note> Thus an Angel appeared vnto <hi>Gideon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg 6.11. to 28.</note> to appoint him to be the ſauiour of Iſrael, out of the <hi>Midianites</hi> hands. Thus the Angel <hi>Raphael</hi> was ſent of God to guide <hi>Tobias</hi> in his wayes,<note place="margin">Tob 5.6. &amp; 1.3.14 15.18.19 20.21.22 Act 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 7 8 9 10 11 12. &amp; 27.23.24</note> and to proſper his buſines. Thus the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels deliuered the Apoſtles out of priſon, and another Angel ſhewed Saint <hi>Paul</hi> that none of them with him in the Ship ſhould periſh. Alſo the Angels miniſtred vnto our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Wildernes after his fourtie dayes faſting.<note place="margin">Mat 4.11.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 22.4.5.</note> And another Angel com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted him in the garden before his apprehenſion.<note place="margin">Mat. 29.24 53.</note> He might like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe haue had legio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Angels to
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:20087:72"/>
deliuer him from the violence of the Iewes, but he would not. Alſo the Angels did tell the <hi>Maries</hi> and the reſt of the deuout women,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.5.6.</note> the newes of our Sauiours reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. In one word,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.7.10.</note> as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels reioyce at the ſinners con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, ſo are they appointed of God for the faithfuls protection, and conſolation; according to that ſaying of the Lord vnto his people:<note place="margin">Exod. 23.20.23. &amp; 32.2</note> 
                  <hi>Behold I ſend an Angel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee to keepe thee in thy way, and to bring thee to the place which I haue prepared.</hi> Finally, our Sauiour teacheth vs in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.10</note> that the Angels are appointed of God to be gardians of little Children. <hi>Iacob</hi> prayed vnto the Lord to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him from the hand of <hi>Eſau,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 32 9.10.11.24.25.28.</note> and the Lord heard him, and in token that he ſhould ouercome his brothers anger, made his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:20087:73"/>
to wreſtle with him, and in the wreſtling ſtrengthned <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſo that the Angell could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile. Thereby giuing him to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that if an Angell was not able to vanquiſh him when as God was on his ſide to ſtrengthen him, how much leſſe ſhould his brother being a mortall man be able to giue him the foile? And therefore the Angell ſaid vnto <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> thy name ſhalbe called <hi>Iacob</hi> no more, but <hi>Iſraell,</hi> becauſe thou haſt had power with God, thou <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>60</label> ſhalt alſo preuaile with men. And herein we are admoniſhed in the time of anguiſh, and aduerſity, but cheifely whenas we are in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril (by reaſon of great men) to haue our recourſe vnto God with <hi>Iacob,</hi> praying him to deliuer vs from the hands of our enemies that are ſtronger then wee. This hath all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:20087:73"/>
beene the cuſtome of the men of God, namely of Godly <hi>Dauid.</hi> Lord how are mine aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries increaſed?<note place="margin">Pſal. 3.1.3.4.5.6.7.</note> (ſaid this holy man when as he fled from his ſon <hi>Abſalon) How many riſe againſt me? But thou Lord art a Buckler for me: my glory, and the lifter vp of mine head. I did call vnto the Lord with my voyce, and he heard me out of his holy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, I laied me downe and ſlept, and roſe vp againe: for the Lord ſuſtained me. I would not be afraid for ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of the people that ſhould beſet me round about. O Lord ariſe, helpe me my God, for thou haſt ſmitten all mine enemies vpon the cheeke-bone: thou haſt broaken the teeth of the wicked.</hi> The Lord was <hi>Dauids</hi> gard againſt the inſurrection of his Sonne, and likewiſe againſt the perſecution of <hi>Saul.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 18.32 to 42.</note> God girded him with ſtrength and taught his hands to
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:20087:74"/>
fight, ſo that he not onely woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his enemies that they were not able to riſe, but alſo conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them, for he beat them as ſmall as the duſt before the winde, and tread them flat as the clay in the ſtreet.</p>
               <p>And as God conſumed <hi>Dauids</hi> enemies, ſo he changed the hearts of <hi>Iacobs</hi> aduerſaries. This great King of hearts ſoftned <hi>Eſaus</hi> heart in his brothers behalfe, for no ſooner came he into his brothers ſight and had done obeiſance in humble manner before him, but as ſoone, God touched <hi>Eſaus</hi> heart with a correſpondent affection, ſo that he ran to meete him, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced him, and fell on his neck, and they wept for ioy out of a kinde tenderneſſe of heart. Thus <hi>Eſau</hi> that once hated his brother mortally, now loued him excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly;
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:20087:74"/>
and he that once intended to kill him, now bleſſeth him; and he that once did baniſh and chaſe him away, now runneth to meete and to embrace him in his armes.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>61</label> In <hi>Eſaus</hi> demeanour we are taught to ouercome all carnall deſire of reuenge, though we haue power to be auenged on ſuch as haue either croſſed vs, or yet done vs any wrong.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.19.20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Dearely beloued</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>auenge not your ſelues, but giue place vnto wrath, for it is written, Vengeance is mine: I wil repay, ſaith the Lord. Therefore if thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my hunger, feede him; if he thirſt, giue him drinke; for in ſo doing thou ſhalt heape coales of fire vpon his head. Be not ouercome of euill, but ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come euill with goodnes.</hi> Againe, in <hi>Iacobs</hi> humble behauiour towards his Brother (for it is ſaid that he bowed himſelfe ſeauen times to
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:20087:75"/>
the ground before his brother whome he called his Lord, and that he ſent him a preſent of his goods that he might finde fauour in his ſight:) In <hi>Iacobs</hi> humility, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>62</label> and curteſie, I ſay, the children of God are taught to vſe all the ordinary meanes of pacifying and appeaſing ſuch as we know to beare vs any euill will, whether by dooing of externall ſubmiſſion and obeiſance, or by vſing hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and reuerent compellations in their behalfe, or yet by giuing or ſending them a preſent of ſuch goods as the Lord hath beſtowed vpon vs. The preſent that <hi>Iacob</hi> ſent vnto his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his bleſſing; inſinuating ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that as it was a bleſſing from God vnto him: ſo ſhould it be a bleſſing to his brother from God by <hi>Iacobs</hi> hands. And it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:20087:75"/>
likely that the Lord bleſſed <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> for <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſake, for being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed towards his brother, and for vſing him ſo kindely as he did, as he likewiſe had bleſſed <hi>Laban</hi> for the ſame <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſake.</p>
               <p>But the pietie and religion of <hi>Iacob</hi> is notable:<note place="margin">Gen. 33.5 11</note> 
                  <hi>God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath had mercie on me, and therefore haue I all things.</hi> Firſt he acknowledgeth his children to be Gods gift, <hi>they are the children</hi> (quoth he to his brother) <hi>whome God of his grace hath giuen thy ſeruant.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen 48.8.9</note> The like ſaid <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> of his ſonnes to his father <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob.</hi> Then his goods he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth to haue them, and holde them of God.<note place="margin">Gen. 32.10</note> 
                  <hi>I am not worthie</hi> (ſaith this worthy man in his prayer vnto God) <hi>of the leaſt of thy mercies, and all the truth, which thou haſt ſhewed vnto thy ſeruant: For with my ſtaffe came Iouer this Iorden, and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:20087:76"/>
now haue I gotten two bands.</hi> He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth Gods mercie and free fauour, and not his owne merite, or any worthynes flowing from his nature to be the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of his good Fortune, and the wel-ſpring of all his wealth. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>63</label> In the which confeſſion and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God ought to imitate him. For God giueth to all, life and breath, and all good things, of his owne free grace in Chriſt Ieſus.<note place="margin">Luk. 21.36 Reuel. 3.4. Epheſ. 4.1.</note> And whatſoeuer worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes there is in vs, it is not of vs, but of him and from him, who hath called vs and tranſlated vs, into the kingdome of his Sonne, and made vs partakers of his rich grace:<note place="margin">2. Cor 3.5. Act. 17 25.28.</note> 
                  <hi>For our ſufficiencie is of God, and in him we liue, we moue and haue our being</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul. Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne bonum Dei donum. Euery good
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:20087:76"/>
giuing</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Iames</hi> another <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob) and euerie perfite gift is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1.17</note> 
                  <hi>and commeth downe from the father of lights.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Iacob</hi> thought it not enough to be religious in a priuate man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but he would alſo make an outward demonſtration of his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie and faith in the ſight of thoſe amongſt whome he liued, and that both for the edifying of men, and for the more celebrious glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of God. And therefore as ſoone as he had bought a parcell of ground in <hi>Schechem</hi> to pitch a Tent vpon, he alſo ſet vp there an Alter, and called it the mightie God of Iſrael. The ſame was the pious practiſe of his religious forefathers, <hi>Iſack</hi> and <hi>Abraham. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> by the erection of this Alter and by giuing it this name,<note place="margin">Gen. 33.18.19.20.</note> would ſhew to the whole world in a moſt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:20087:77"/>
publike and open manner, that he did confeſſe and profeſſe that all his might, ſtrength, power, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie and hap, was the meere gift of God who loued him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>64</label> he was borne. And herein we are taught, whenſoeuer we do receiue at Gods hands any nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble benefite and bleſſing ſpirituall or temporall, as of ſafetie, and proſperitie, that we endeuour by all meanes not onely to proue thankefull therefore in a priuate manner, but alſo to make as pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like a demonſtration of our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes as we poſſibly can, as by building or repairing of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, for the honour of God, or of hoſpitalls and almes houſes for the help and reliefe of the poore. <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine</hi> (ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour) <hi>before men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat 5.16. Philip. 2.15</note> 
                  <hi>that they ſeeing your good workes may glorifie your
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:20087:77"/>
father which is heauen.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſee that deuoute <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 22.22 25 &amp; 116.12 13.14.17 18.19</note> ſaith not onely that he would praiſe God publikely in the midſt of the congregation, but alſo that he would performe his vowes in the ſight of them that feare him, euen in the preſence of all his people.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe when at the Lords appointment godly <hi>Iacob</hi> went to dwell in <hi>Bethel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 35.1.2.3.4.5.</note> there he alſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected an Alter vnto God that appeared vnto him when as he fled from his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> and heard him in the day of his tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, and was with him in the way which he went. And not onely this, but he alſo comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all thoſe of his houſhold to put away all ſtrange Gods from them, and to clenſe themſelues, and to change their garments. For
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:20087:78"/>
it doth appeare that there were ſome of his ſeruants which had beene brought vp in Idolatrie in the land of <hi>Haran</hi> where he had ſerued his vncle <hi>Laban.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 31.19.30.</note> Who like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe him ſelfe was not free from that ſinne: as may appeare by that it is recorded how that <hi>Rahel Labans</hi> daughter, and <hi>Iacobs</hi> wife ſtole away her fathers Idoles, the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>65</label> which <hi>Laban</hi> calleth his Gods. Wherein may be eſpied the great madnes and blindenes of men, in making vnto themſelues ſuch Gods as are not able to keepe themſelues from the ſtealing hands of theeues.<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.4.5.6.7.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Their Idoles</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>are ſiluer and gold, euen the worke of mens hands:</hi> they are golden Gods, made of gold, not able to make golde: made by men, not able to make a man: no nor yet the leaſt worme creeping vpon
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:20087:78"/>
the earth: all which, the true God doth. They are dumbe Gods, for though they haue a mouth, they cannot ſpeake, much leſſe are they able to make the dumbe to ſpeake. They are blinde Gods, for though they haue eyes, yet they cannot ſee, much leſſe are they able to make the blinde to ſee. They are deafe Gods, for though they haue cares, yet can they not heare, much leſſe are they able to make the deafe to heare. They are ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les &amp; dead Gods, for though they haue noſes, yet they cannot ſmell, though they haue hands, yet can they not touch, though they haue feete, yet can they not walke, though they haue a throte, yet make they no ſound: and in one word, though they haue the whole lineaments of a man, yet haue they no ſparkle of the life of man: how
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:20087:79"/>
much leſſe haue they of the life of the euerliuing God? <hi>They that make them are like vnto them: ſo are all that truſt in them.</hi> Euen more ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and blockiſh then ſtockes or ſtones.<note place="margin">Iſai. 44.9.10.11.12.13.14.15 16.17.18.19.20.</note> And therefore the Lord by his Prophet promiſeth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found theſe ſhop-gods of ſtone and timber, and theſe forge-gods of golde and ſiluer; euen all theſe vaine hand-made Gods, together with the fond and fooliſh God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers.</p>
               <p>Thus in the perſon of <hi>Iacob</hi> are all maiſters of families taught to take care, that the onely true God be acknowledged and worſhiped of their whole houſhold. For it is a verie hard thing me thinketh that the man that worſhipeth a falſe God, ſhould proue a true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant in his maiſters behalfe. It ought then to be their chiefe care
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:20087:79"/>
to ſee that their ſeruants be ſuch as ſerue God, and feare him, by the meanes both of a pious and chriſtian profeſſion, and of a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and honeſt conuerſaſion. For if they feare God ſincerely, it can not be but they wil ſerue their maiſters likewiſe for Gods ſake, and in him, conſcionably &amp; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. Thus the Lord who loued <hi>Iacob</hi> before he was borne, was feared, loued and honoured of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> after he was borne: and not onely of him, but alſo of his whole houſhold. And therfore the Lord not onely honoured him with his preſence in appearing vnto him,<note place="margin">Gen. 35.9.13.15.22.</note> &amp; bleſſing him, but he alſo bleſſed his ſeede for his ſake. <hi>I am God all ſufficient</hi> (ſaith the Lord vnto his ſeruant) <hi>grow and multiply, a nation and a multitude of nations ſhall ſpring of thee, and kings ſhall come out of thy
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:20087:80"/>
loynes. Alſo I will giue thee the land which I gaue to Abraham and Iſack, euen vnto thee and thy ſeed after thee.</hi> The Lord bleſſed him likewiſe with a great iſſue, and gaue him twelue Sonnes, for whoſe vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous education he was exceeding carefull. For he tooke order that they ſhould not ſpend their young yeeres in idlenes, but ſhould be occupied about cattel euen from their child-hood. And as he did with great diligence incourage them to vertue, ſo did he not faile to correct them, and ſharply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue them when as they did offend, or fall into any vice: as he did <hi>Reuben</hi> for his vncleannes,<note place="margin">Gen. 34.1.7.25.26.27.28.29.30.31. &amp; 35.22. &amp; 49.4.5.6.7.</note> &amp; <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui</hi> with the reſt of their brethren for their reuenge wrought vpon the <hi>Shechemites</hi> for <hi>Shechems</hi> deflowring of their ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Dinah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:20087:80"/>And heerein are all fathers and mothers taught, to be verie watchfull and carefull for the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous education and honeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of their children.</p>
               <p>Thus we read how that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> commanded his children to keepe the way of the Lord.<note place="margin">Gen. 18.19</note> And how that <hi>Moſes</hi> did exhort the people of <hi>Iſraell</hi> to teach their children how they ought to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and keepe Gods ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and becauſe that <hi>Eli</hi> the high Prieſt and Iudge of <hi>Iſraell</hi> did not correct his ſonnes more ſharply then he did for their ſinne;<note place="margin">Deut. 4.9 14.20. &amp; 32.46.</note> and tooke not ſo great paines as he ought to reclaime them from their lewde and wicked waies, therefore the Lord ſaid thus vnto <hi>Eli.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 22.31.32 33.34</note> 
                  <hi>Behould the daies come that I will cut off thine arme and the arme of thy others houſe, that there ſhall not be an
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:20087:81"/>
old man in thine houſe for euer. And this ſhall be a ſigne vnto thee, that ſhall come vpon thy two ſonnes</hi> Hoph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, <hi>and</hi> Phinehas: <hi>in one day they ſhall both die.</hi> And afterward the Lord ſhewed <hi>Samuel</hi> what ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of <hi>Eli</hi> and his houſe.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 3.11.12 13 14.</note> 
                  <hi>I will iudge his houſe for euer, for the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity which he knoweth, becauſe his ſonnes ran into a ſlander and he staied them not.</hi> And behold the iſſue of the Lords commination and threatning!<note place="margin">1. Sam 4 11.17.18.19.20.21 22.</note> In one day <hi>Elies</hi> two inſolent ſonnes were ſlaine of the Philiſtims in the field. And old <hi>Eli</hi> hearing of his ſonnes death, and of the taking of the Arke of God (the tidings wherof grieued him moſt) fell from his ſeate backwards by the ſide of the gate, ſo that his neck brake, and he died. Beſides that which befell vnto his daughter in law, who no ſooner
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:20087:81"/>
heard the report that the Arke of God was taken, and that her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in law and her husband were dead, but ſhe was ſtricken with ſuch a ſorrow, that ſhe trauailed before her time, and died when as ſhe had named the childe <hi>Icha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hod,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The glory is departed from Iſraell; for the Arke of God is taken.</hi> So great is the anger of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Parents for their negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in correcting and directing their children as they ought; and therefore wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> doth dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and treble his admonitions and exhortations to Parents, that they neglect not this great duty. <hi>He that ſpareth his rodd,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro 13 24 &amp; 19.18. &amp; 22.15. &amp; 23.13. &amp; 29.15.</note> 
                  <hi>hateth his ſon: but he that loueth him chaſteneth him betime. Chaſten thy ſonne while there is yet hope, and let not thy ſoule ſpare for his murmuring. Fooliſhnes is bound in the heart of a childe, but the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:20087:82"/>
rodd of correction ſhall driue it away from him, withhould not therefore correction from the childe, for if thou ſmite him with the rodd, he ſhall not die. The rodd and correction giue wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but a childe ſet at liberty maketh his mother aſhamed.</hi> The ſumme of all is this, that the rodd hath a certaine efficacy to driue away fooliſhnes and fondnes out of the heads of children, and to driue in wiſedome and vertue into their hearts. And that if the father ſmite his childes body with the birchen rod of temporal correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Sathan ſhall not ſmite his ſoule with the bruiſing, yron rod of eternall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. To the ſame purpoſe <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Sirach</hi> in his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome exhorteth Parents not to bring vp their children delicately and wantonly, nor to giue them too much liberty, nor yet to
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:20087:82"/>
withhould from them due cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 30.1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10 11.12.13.</note> 
                  <hi>He that loueth his ſonne</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>cauſeth him oft to feele the rodd, that he may haue ioy of him in the end. He that chaſtiſeth his ſonne ſhall haue ioy in him, and ſhall reioyce of him among his acquaintance. He that teacheth his ſonne, grieueth the enemie, and before his friends he ſhall reioyce of him. Though his father die, yet is he as though he were not dead: for he hath left one behinde him that is like him. In his life he ſaw him, and had ioy in him, and was not ſorie in his death, neither was he aſhamed before his enemies. He left behinde him an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger againſt his enemies, &amp; one that ſhould ſhew fauour vnto his friends. He that flattereth his ſonne bindeth vp his wounds, and his heart is greiued at euery crie. An vntamed horſe will be ſtubborne, and a wanton childe will be wilfull. If thou bring vp thy ſonne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licately,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:20087:83"/>
he ſhall make thee affraid: and if thou play with him, he ſhall bring thee to heauineſſe. Laugh not with him leſt thou be ſorry with him: and leſt thou gnaſh thy teeth in the end. Giue him not libertie in his youth, and wink not at his folly. Bow downe his necke while he is yong, and beate him on the ſides while he is a childe, leaſt he wax ſtubborne &amp; he diſobedient vnto thee, and ſo bring ſorrow vnto thine heart: chaſtiſe thy child, and be diligent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, leaſt his ſhame grieue thee.</hi> And the ſame wiſe man in another place,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7 23 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.27.28.</note> as he exhorteth the childe to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour his father with his whole heart, and not to forget the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of his mother, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that he was borne of them, and that he cannot recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence them the things that they haue done for him: So he adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth parents to inſtruct their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:20087:83"/>
and to holde their necke from their youth: to keepe their daughters bodie, and not to ſhew their face cheerefull towards them, and to marry them to men of vnderſtanding. Finally (ſaith the wiſe man) <hi>if children liue honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 22.8 9.</note> 
                  <hi>they ſhall put away the ſhame of their parents: But if children be proud with hautines and fooliſhnes, they defile the nobility of their kindred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee then the great ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the rod in a diſcreet parents hand. <hi>Moſes</hi> Rod lifted vp,<note place="margin">Exo 14 10 21.22.</note> deuided the waters, &amp; made dry ground to appeare in the mides of the Sea, to giue the children of Iſrael paſſage to the land of Canaan. And the fathers or mothers rod being lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon their children, will be a meanes to deuide the waters of the waywardnes &amp; wantonnes of their yong yeares, &amp; to calme the raging
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:20087:84"/>
ſea of their vnruly paſſions, and fleſhly afflictions. Whereby their ſoule may walke as it were on drie ground ſecurely, and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without any impediment to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the land of the heauenly <hi>Canaan.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 17.5</note> And as <hi>Moſes</hi> rod brought forth water out of the hard Rocke being ſmitten therewith: ſo ſhall the parents rod not onely bring forth of the rockie nature of their children, the teares of Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but alſo turne the ſtonie hardnes and obſtinatenes of their ſtubborne inclination, into the ſtreamie ſoftnes of a docible diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. The Rod or tree which <hi>Moſes</hi> did caſt into the waters of Marah,<note place="margin">Exod 15.23.24.25.</note> made the bitter water ſweete. And the rod of Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will turne the bitternes of the childes nature into the ſweetnes of a dutifull behauiour. Finally,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:20087:84"/>
as <hi>Aarons</hi> rod budded,<note place="margin">Num. 17.8</note> &amp; brought forth bloſſomes and beare ripe Almonds: So the teaching Rod (for <hi>Aaron</hi> ſignifieth a teacher) of fathers, mothers and Schoolmai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, will make children to bring forth the buddes and bloſſoms of an hopefull behauiour in their yong yeeres; and to beare the ripe Almonds of honeſt and religious actions in their riper yeeres.</p>
               <p>Let not Parents then ſpare the rod; for the rod vſed with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, is a meanes to bring children vnto God. I ſay, with diſcretion; becauſe Parents and preceptors muſt not kill children with cruelry, but correct the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with lenity: they muſt not ouercharge them rudely with the blowes of indignation; but chaſten them ruthfully with the ſtripes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. In one word, corrections
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:20087:85"/>
muſt not ſerue for the deſtruction of the body, but for the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Soule. And if it chance that a child be of ſo gentle &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous a diſpoſition that he may be reclaimed or wonne with faire perſwaſions, and gentle enduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and allurements, then were it but meere madnes to vſe any roughnes or auſtere ſharpnes in his behalfe: And therfore as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren muſt harken diligently vnto the exhortation of the Apoſtle; <hi>Children obey your parents in the Lord:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.1.2.3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>For this is right; honour thy father and thy mother (which is the firſt commandement with promiſe) that it may be well with thee, and that thou maiſt liue long on the earth.</hi> So muſt parents liſten vnto the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of the ſame Apoſtle thus, <hi>and yee fathers prouoke not your children to wrath: but bring them vp
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:20087:85"/>
in inſtruction and information of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither muſt they faile to bring them vp in ſome lawfull calling, and rather in ſome mechanicall trade and manuall occupation, then that they ſhould liue idle: for ſo did <hi>Iacob</hi> bring vp his Sons. So that when as <hi>Pharao</hi> ſaid vnto them, <hi>What is your trade?</hi> they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the king,<note place="margin">Gen 47.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy ſeruants are ſheep-heards, both we and our fathers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prouer. 27.23.24.25 26.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Be diligent to know the ſtate of thy flocke,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) and take heede to the heardes, for riches remaine not alwayes, nor the crowne from genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to generation. The hay diſcouereth it ſelfe, and the graſse appeareth, and the hearbes of the mountaines are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered. The Lambes are for thy cloathing, and the Goates are the price of the field. And let the milke of the Goates be ſufficient for thy foode, for
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:20087:86"/>
the foode of thy familie, and for the ſuſtenance of thy maides. Hate not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious worke</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ieſus</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Sirach) neither the husbandrie which the most high hath created.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.15 22.</note> 
                  <hi>And if thou haue cattell, looke well to them.</hi> Neither let a man be aſhamed of a mechanicall trade, for we ſee that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> the husband of <hi>Marie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 13.55 Mar. 6.3. Luk. 2.51. Mat. 4.18.19.20.21. &amp; 8.23.24. Luk. 4.4.5 Act. 18.1.2.3. Exod. 28.3 &amp; 31.2.3.4.5.6. &amp; 35.30.31.32 33.34.35.</note> and <hi>Ieſus</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Marie,</hi> yea, the Sonne of God diſdained not to play the Carpenter. And the Apoſtles were fiſher-men, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> was a maker of Tents. And it is recorded of <hi>Bezaleel</hi> and <hi>Aholeab</hi> two Tradeſ-men that God gaue them much knowledge in mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall things, euen filled them with an excellent ſpirit of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, vnderſtanding, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in all work-manſhip, to worke curiouſly in gold, ſiluer, braſſe, in grauing, and ſetting of
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:20087:86"/>
ſtones, in hewing and caruing of wood, in working of broydred and needle worke in blue Silke, in Purple, in Scarlet, and in fine linnen: finally in weauing and working of all manner of curious work man-ſhip. Let no man I ſay then be aſhamed of a mechanicall Trade or craft, ſeeing it is a gift of Gods ſpirit, and that (as <hi>Siracides</hi> ſaith) <hi>in the hands of the crafts-man ſhall the workes be commended.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.19</note>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer,<note place="margin">Gen 36.7.</note> the Lord bleſſed <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> with abundance of ſubſtance and ſtore; with cattell, Sheepe, Beeues, Camels, and Aſſes in great number, as he had done his father <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſack</hi> before.<note place="margin">Gen. 41. &amp; 45. &amp; 46. &amp; 47.</note> And in the time of the great and long famine of ſeauen yeeres that was throughout the world, God prouided for <hi>Iacob and his houſhould</hi> by the hand of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> his ſonne,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:20087:87"/>
whome the Lord vnwitting his father &amp; brethren, had preferred to be ruler ouer all <hi>Egipt</hi> next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the King. Thus the holy man as he was bleſſed of God for his godly liuing, and ſpent his daies in bleſſing of God: So he ended them in bleſſing of God, and in bleſſing of his children in the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>68</label> name of God. Teaching by his example all fathers and mothers, liuing and dying, to doe the like in the behalfe of their children; and that they teach them to know and acknowledge that all bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes both ſpirituall and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, is the fruite and effect of Gods bleſſing of them: and that therefore the praiſe of our whole happines muſt be aſcribed vnto God:<note place="margin">Eccle. 44.23.24.</note> euen vnto him who (as <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Sirach</hi> ſpeaketh in <hi>Iacobs</hi> praiſe) <hi>cauſed the bleſſing
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:20087:87"/>
of all men to reſt vpon the head of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, and made himſelfe knowen by his bleſſings and gaue him an heritage, and deuided his portions, and parted them amongst the twelue tribes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
